He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc.
Chapter 48.
Verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons.
and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage
with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment
in creation. The union of the scene and uns...
as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, greetings, giant killers and dragon slayers.
You are listening to the 125th episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Why would you put yourself through this?
Nevertheless, I am Father Andrew Steamedamaik and with me
is the only person who has ever broadcast live on ancient faith radio
from the inner sanctum of his water closet.
The one and only father Stephen D. Young.
And together we are still tired from the Lord of Spirit's conference.
So these I am speaking on the left for yourself.
I know having having escaped with my life, I find myself
innervated.
Though my spirits are somewhat dampened by once again, having to go on
after the enane ramblings of that paltrune who they keep putting on before us.
It's true.
I don't understand how it is that that guy is still.
I mean, I told them to remove that show.
But I mean it's cheap content, but other than that. Yeah. Yeah. It's good filler. Yeah. Well anyway, it's like episodes of ridiculousness on MTV 2, right? Like you just we got a whole the schedule.
Oh, I forgot about MTV 2 and MTV. Let's celebrate 15 years of music.
And then 30 years of something.
Except the M doesn't stand for anything.
But we are.
We are live and starting in the second half of the show if you're joining us live you can call us at 855 237 2346
If you make it past the great gatekeeper
Mike Massaged and again
With your on topic question we might even talk back or we could just listen if your question is a little off topic just lie
Wow, you see that's because there's no deontological ethics on this show, right?
I've not even do that
We are continuing in the theme of ancient empires that show up in the Bible and tonight
it is all about Persia so quick pull Father Stephen cats or rugs.
Those who are in the know know that the correct answer to this question is actually chandeliers.
Oh.
Ah.
My peeps in LA know what I'm talking about.
Bold.
Channeling teen farcey programming.
Wow, you know what I look
done Guam, we got Los Angeles TV because this is back in the late 80s and we would get
there's a Los Angeles cable station that would record their all their programming and then
ship it over to Guam on VHS tapes and they would all get played a week late. So like when
you're opening up the Disney Channel schedule, you always add have add like plus seven. So
it's like being old counterists, you know, except for cable TV. And there was no international
all things for you so
There was not, there was not, there was very few really like satellite live TV, but a lot
of people were absent from school on Super Bowl Monday.
So that was one thing that we did have.
But I mean, I remember watching, you know, ads for KCOP, Los Angeles.
Yes.
There on Guam.
Which I'm sure you did too.
So there you go.
Our childhoods connected in this.
Well, they had this double television.
Yeah.
that was like
the catch all channel for Middle Eastern and Asian immigrants. So there were these, it was a
UHF, those of you old enough to know what that even means anymore, aside from the Weird Al Yankovic movie.
There's a UHF channel. So it was on the dial that went like, Braap when you turned it.
Yes. Yes. And then you had a fiddle with the fine tuning forever.
But uh, channel E.T.
would have like a block of farcey programming and then like a block of like Korean programming
and then like a block of Chinese programming.
Our local alcohol distributor, beer distributor right here in Emmaus is owned by a Persian
guy and one time our mutual friend Dr. Jenkins went in there and said, you know, your Persian
he says yes, yes I am.
He says, are you Muslim?
He says, yep, I am.
And he says, and you.
you own this place that sells alcohol?
Says, we don't sell alcohol here.
We sell heavenly beverages.
So I guess I should have added that to my poll, heavenly beverages.
You know, ask, ask if he has a chandelier.
Trust me.
Trust me on this one.
I ask if he has a chandelier.
I might someone in the YouTube chat claims that Bart Irman flew over his house.
I don't know what that means, but...
Did you see a video?
No.
I'm trying to decide if this person is suffering from psychosis or if he just lives near
Bart Irman.
I, another person claims that Bart Irman is walking his dog in their neighborhood.
So, so he's now like Elvis or Bigfoot or something.
We're going to have Bart Irman's side.
Bart Irman's side would be a thing now.
Yeah.
It's totally a thing.
Okay.
I hope he, uh,
Steers clear of certain of our listening audience. So, so tell us all about ancient Persia, Uncle Steve.
All about all because we're most we're mostly talking about one particular guy actually. Yeah. Yeah. And and particularly how Persia connects with the Bible. Right. And so this, this episode is a is a little different.
Um,
And
then the last one we were talking about,
Nebuchadnezzar in that,
as we talked about that time,
Nebuchadnezzar kind of was the Dio Babylonian Empire,
right?
Like, yeah, his dad started the thing rolling.
And yeah, there was a quick succession of emperors
over a handful of years after him,
the last of which we're going to meet this evening.
But he was kind of it. And so and the Neobabalone Empire frankly wasn't around for that long.
So we kind of talked about the whole thing. Whereas the Persian Empire, the original Persian Empire,
the one we're going to be talking about tonight is started by the guy who were mainly talking about
tonight, Cyrus the Great, but actually goes on for a fair spell.
that until Alexander the Great shows up. And with the exception of a couple bits in Daniel
and some obviously the events of Esther, there's not a ton of old testament
literature from the Persian period per se. Most of the old
testament books that you find in, for example, Orthodox and Roman Catholic Old
Testaments and Oriental Orthodox Old Testaments are actually come from the Greek
period. Yeah. So while the Persian period is longer than the neo-Bavillonian
period. There isn't as much to talk about once you get past Syru.
So Cyrus, who we're talking about tonight, we're going to talk about him.
We're going to talk about the founding of the original Persian Empire because there's another one later.
We're talking about the founding of the original Persian Empire, but we're not going to talk about
its whole history. We're not really going to talk about its successors because what we're aiming at,
which of course we won't get to until the third half, is the importance of Cyrus and the Bible,
and Cyrus is important in...
the Hebrew Bible. Pretty much as important I would argue as Nebuchadnezzar despite, you know,
differing historical situation. So, yeah. So, roughly, what we're doing tonight is like
what we did last time, but roughly, it's going to differ in some respects.
That's it.
So the Persian Empire we're talking about, like we said, is the original Persian Empire,
the first one, which is known as the Accomended Empire, we'll get into why here in just a second.
The other Persian Empire that you will read in here about is the Sassanid Persian Empire.
The Sasseted Persian Empire is post-Christian period.
Okay, so it rises up when the the eastern part of the Roman Empire starts showing weakness.
And it sort of comes into being and that's where you get the wars like if if you were in
church last month now already for the feast of the exultation of the cross and you paid
attention to like the cynic saryan and stuff and it talked about the bison gene emperor.
or the Roman Emperor, sorry guys,
fighting the Persians, that's the Sassanid Persians,
that's the later Persians.
That's the like third to seventh century AD.
Yeah.
So that's post-Christian era
and they get wiped out basically by the Muslims.
So but tonight we're talking about the original one,
that committed empire that gets wiped out.
by the Greeks. So key difference. Um, was Alexander a Greek? Sorry. Just wanted to mess
with the certain you're going to start this Macedonia stuff, aren't you? Yeah, there
you go. Just stir that pot. Stir that call in and tell father Andrew what you think about
that. Macedon. I'll just go home and we can, you can listen to some very angry people
rest is you.
The, and this Persian Empire, so we've talked about, because we're talking about the Neobabalone
and Empire last time, and how they kind of took over the Assyrian Empire in its waning
days.
And of course, we know a little bit about the Greeks.
Obviously, we think about the Roman Empire every day if you're like me.
But the Persian Empire historically is...
very different category than the Assyrian and Neobabalone and Empires. This is an empire in a
different sense. So both the Assyrian and Neobabalone and Empires are empires in the true sense of
the term empire, which means they're, they consist of conquered territory. So they are empires,
Bye.
especially in the Assyria Empire, there wasn't a lot of infrastructure. Right? Like the taxation was more like extortion.
Right? Was your city needs to said this much tribute or we're going to come and you know, raise you to the ground kind of thing.
Not sort of an advanced system of taxation.
There was not a lot of emphasis on establishing trade in commerce routes among
the Assyrians. Yeah, I mean, that was just not their thing.
Yeah, I'd call it kleptocracy, but that's not quite what that word means.
But it was an empire based on stealing and pillaging and whatever.
Yeah. Now, never never could desert wanted, right?
Clearly had aspirations to more, right? I mean, the neo-Babalone and Empire,
its whole sort of race on debt was we're going to reestablish the Babylonian
The Empire of...
right of the Bronze Age. Yeah, and we've talked about that original Babylonian empire, the level of global commerce that facilitated and and all of that, right? And that's what Nebuchadise wanted to recreate.
But the Neopabolonian Empire fundamentally wasn't around long enough and did not have any talented people after Nebuchadise right to actually pull that off.
off or even really beginning.
get there, right? But the Persian Empire that Cyrus is going to found is going to accomplish
that, right? They are going to accomplish that. And it's height and it's furthest extent,
okay? Which is under a derrius or if you're being fancy in British, derias. The second,
I prefer Darius because, you know, we don't want to call the guy Hoody.
Um, the, the, uh, that farthest extent under Darius II, the Persian Empire controlled
Egypt and Ethiopia in Africa, all of Asia Minor and into the Greek coast and the Balkans
in Europe.
All the way across what's now Afghanistan and Pakistan up into what's now Uzbekistan
in Kazakhstan.
all the way into India, not up to India, into India, the western chunk of India.
And this was, you know, we're talking about the sixth century
and the beginning of the fifth century BC that they controlled this territory.
Yeah, and if anyone wants to know, see that in a map, there is a good map on the Wikipedia article
of the Accommoded Empire.
And you can just see how much territory it was.
I mean, it's pretty, pretty huge.
Yeah, like the portrait of the globe.
Right.
Like all the way to Libya and Egypt.
Yeah, I mean, it's crazy.
So that, that level of territorial control is even beyond the first
Babylonian empire and isn't going to be seen again until sort of the peak of the Roman
empire.
Alexander is going to come.
conquer pretty much all of that, but he's not going to ever rule it. Right. And it's
going to get chopped up by his successors. So, but as impressive as the amount of territory
is the fact that the Persians set up an administrative state that actually governs all that.
Yeah. We're a significant amount of time.
Yes, bureaucracy trade routes.
They're moving things around right.
And so that level of infrastructure, again, is the kind of thing that you hadn't been
seen in the world since the original Babylonian Empire.
And again, you got to go to the Romans doing stuff like building the aqueducts and this
kind of thing before you see this kind of thing again.
So, as promised, why is it called the accommod-
Empire. So it's called that because the dynasty that Cyrus, the second Cyrus, the great was a part of,
was started by Achaemenis. So it's literally just named after a dude.
And he is this founder figure who as each generation goes past Looms larger and larger.
Yeah. And to the point that even though most of the later emperors are not going to be
biologically related to him, they're all going to want to prove that they're biologically related to him.
Yeah. Apparently his name in Persian might be pronounced something like
Aximonish, which I don't know, that sounds a little bit more metal than the
the chimneys.
which is definitely a Hellenized version of the name.
Yeah, Hellenized version.
Yeah.
Yes.
A guy, many.
That's a...
Hacks up.
So, don't name your kids that, though, people.
Yeah, no.
This guy's a pagan.
This is the...
Yes, right.
And not even that prominent of a pagan.
That's true, that's true.
So, other than that, he's...
So he becomes this kind of legendary figure, like a Greek hero, or like a demi-god.
Yeah.
or one of the gibberim, right? He becomes one of those figures who sort of looms large as the one
with the royal blood, right? They get passed out. And so he was the king of Parsifan,
which was the sort of main city in the region of Pars on the Iranian Plateau. Pars being
where like
like Parthian and Persian come from.
And I'm a lot.
And Parse.
Or those who want to go down that particular rabbit hole.
And so he then though, even though he is that, he then becomes, there's a larger city
in the region called Anshin.
became the king of ancient also and then king of ancient until
Cyrus the second, Cyrus the Great. King of Anshon becomes the title that the dynasty uses.
I know that doesn't sound impressive to us because we don't know where Anshon is.
Anson Mounts plays Captain Pike, but he was not alive yet.
But the King of Anshon becomes sort of their primary title. And so
So the sort of success...
session goes from a fellow named Tyspees to Cyrus, who's Cyrus the first, not our Cyrus yet.
Cyrus the first, to Cambesys the first, his son, and then Cambesys the first, his son
is Cyrus the second, who becomes Cyrus the Great.
There's a bunch of debate about whether that was his given name originally or whether he
took that name.
when he became king or some kind of title or yeah, how all that worked, but either at his
birth or at the point where he becomes, you know, Prince Regent or what have you, he's
named after his grandfather.
Cyrus I.
Yeah.
And so his family up to him basically are the rulers of the Iranian Plateau.
to their immediate west is the kingdom of the mead.
Okay, so remember last time we talked about one of the ways that
Navinitis
The
Not Navinitis Navipulacir
We'll get to that one of those now. What about you?
Another one of those Naboo theoporix
David Paul, David Polasser, who was Dominican
Ezra's father, right?
the ways that he was able to overcome the Assyrians was by making a treaty with the King of the
Meads. Right? So the Meads who had been operating sort of as mercenaries, they started sacking,
since a week this they started sacking Assyrian cities. And so Nabopalassir cut this deal with them
And to fight with his army, that's how helped him to defeat the Assyrians.
And so in return...
they were given territory on the eastern end, basically, to the east of the neo-bavilonian
empire proper. And from the perspective of the Meeds, right, hey, it's territory, king
of the Meeds, I got my kingdom now, right? I got my territory where I'm the boss, kind
Independence they're not part of the Neobabalone Empire
but from the perspective of the Neobabalonean emperors,
if you get into the history,
and we've only touched on this here and there, I know,
but the history of Mesopotamia,
of Sumer and Akkad,
they were constantly getting invaded from the east
by the Elohimites and by other people.
I think in our Abraham episode,
we talked about this a little,
some of the invasions,
leading up to the earth.
period. Anyway, so they're constantly getting invaded from the east. And so from the perspective
of the neo-babolonian empire, giving the meads this territory, the meads now are sort of this
buffer state, right? Although they're not really a nation state, I know. But they're sort of this
buffer region, right? Between any potential invaders from the east and the neo-babolonian empire
itself right they're gonna have to go through the needs to get to the
the Dio Babylonian Empire, giving them time to call up an army, etc., etc.
And the Meads are no slouches at fighting.
So that's sort of the deal on that side.
And so that represented a fairly potent check on the early ambitions of these Persian kings before Cyrus.
to get to most of the rest.
of civilization where things are sort of happening at that point in history, they'd have to go through
the meads, which they're not going to do. And then to their east and their north, you've got a lot
of nothing. You got a lot of sparsely populated tribal lands. And if you go far enough east, you run into
India and India was established enough at this point that they weren't going to be taken any territory
from India yet.
their mind. Right. So these early kings before Cyrus the second are not super ambitious
territorially. They're not really trying to start an empire yet. There are a couple steps
above warlord, but yeah. They have cities, right? And they're, you know, yeah. And they
have a domain. It's just not a big domain. And there's not really room for them to easily
expand. Until...
Cyrus the second comes along.
Dun dun.
And he's the son of Ken Beese's the first.
Um,
so it terms of what his name means.
Yeah, I'm sure that there are dissertations and many journal articles.
Oh, yes.
Yes, etymology.
So for a lot of the stuff we're talking a lot of the stuff we're talking about
tonight.
We're going to try and indicate like different sources on different things.
A lot of stuff we're talking about today.
Our primary historical sources on a lot of this are Greek historians.
Yeah.
Now we also have some actual old Persian inscriptions and stuff.
Right. We're going to talk about some of those.
So we have those and those help us with dates and different things.
Right.
So we have these benchmarks beyond just what the Greeks say.
We have these kind of benchmarks.
Dates, benchmark dates.
clue us in a little bit on this and help us orient what the Greeks are saying. But some of this stuff,
the Greeks say, seems unreliable, shall we say. In the sense that they were deeply fascinated by this
figure of Cyrus. Because of course they're going to come into contact with some of his
his successors.
with the Persians.
And so, you know, go watch 300.
It's a documentary.
It's totally a...
It's like the reason why, of course, is that Persia was this...
Just to reiterate this, was this massive, complex, stupifying the huge state, you know,
with armies of like when the Persians went up against the Greeks.
they had like hundreds of thousands of troops on the ground, which is just, you know,
boggling.
It's part of 300 that's exaggerated, but not false is the fact that they would bring
like Indian and African elephants.
Yeah.
Right.
It's a battle.
like the person's so up with these monstrous creatures right?
Right, which, you know, to Greeks had never seen before.
Yeah, exactly.
Like, these are monsters that they have clearly summoned from the underworld or something.
Yes, for the far quarters of the globe.
Right.
Because even the Greeks do it was a globe.
Like, right.
So yeah, this was, this was incredible.
And, and Alexander the Great, Cyrus was his role model.
Cyrus the Great was his role model.
Like he did about did everything he could to find out everything he could about Cyrus.
That's who he patterned himself after. Um, so they look at the Greek writers.
You could tell look at Cyrus with like kind of this fear and awe and reverence,
right? Which means stories about him get distorted in a couple of ways, you know?
Yes. Like sort of he sort of like Paul Bunyan or something like Superman.
you get those kind of just
But you also get these sort of like horrifying monstrous
distortions, too, like, right?
We'll give you an example here in a minute.
Larger than life.
Larger than larger than life.
Yes.
And so.
Double triple Excel than life.
That's what I say.
What I say.
That's what I mean.
You know, we have these Greek accounts.
But we also have these other inscriptions
scriptures from
the Persians at the time and stuff that kind of are a check on some of the excesses of
some of those accounts, right?
Then let us know that they may be excesses, right?
Yeah.
But so that also means things like what his name means, right?
The Greeks, of course, tell us ancient etymologies are famously unreliable, especially from ancient
Greeks.
But so fun.
gives bogus at about
all the time. Yeah. Like as arguments, oh, well, you see this word comes from this word,
which means that it is like, no, it literally does not know. But to their credit, to their
credit, and this made this may surprise a lot of people. Persian is an Indo-European language.
I mean, that's part of the Indo part of the whole thing. Yeah, like Greek or like English or,
you know, yeah, most of most European languages are in the same language family that Persian is in.
Yes.
And that helps.
Yeah.
Right?
Because that means when they look at old Greek roots, sometimes those old Greek roots are
related to the old Persian roots.
I mean, there's some stuff that's cognate too.
My wife actually took Persian for a while in undergrad.
And she told me about a joke that they were making in the class that was playing off of the
fact that the Persian word for mouse is mush, which, you know, right away you can hear
that it's similar.
So even cogniz between English
person, how about that everybody? Yeah, yeah. And so we get Cyrus. So Cyrus is a Latinization
of Kairos, Giros, yeah, yeah, Giros, yeah. That's Kyros, yeah. Might be like from Kuros,
sure that's how I heard a person say it.
So this is what theory, which is basically the word for sun, right, like the sun in the
sky.
Yeah, right.
And the reason the Greeks all endorsed this because I know you're thinking like Eulios,
but there is an older, there is an archaic Greek term for the sun, right?
it is.
uh, Kuros. Not Kuros. Yeah. That's um, so if that's the case, then Cyrus would probably actually
be derived from Kurovash, an old Persian, which would be the one like the sun. Um, you are my sunshine
as it were.
And this would probably fit, especially in terms of like his grandfather, because at that point,
it seems very likely where you get into this war to the second half, but you're dealing with
early, you're dealing with still the pagan phase of Persian religion. By the way, I just looked
this up, because I was really curious. So Helios, which you mentioned, is actually cognate
with the Persian...
Quar or whatever how it's pronounced so they are ultimately from the same proto-indio-European route. Yeah, so there you go
So yeah, so at least this only requires the Greeks to be aware of their own language group
Yeah, yeah, yeah, and not Egyptian or something right right not related
But of course
We don't have anything that proves that it just kind of makes sense. It's probably
the majority opinion we're going with it, right? If you want to go and read any of the countless
journal articles suggesting other possibilities, enjoy. But so Eddie's born circa 600 BC, like 600,
599 somewhere in there. And we know about that because we know when he succeeds to the throne and
then we know how old he was when he succeeded.
to the throne. And he was married off to, uh, well, there's there's no way to get around
it. Uh, listen up game of Thrones fans. Uh, he gets he's married to his aunt. I mean, this
is not super uncommon that day. No, it really, it really wasn't at that time. Um, because
Remember, the Accomended.
right? Like it's the royal blood, right? Yeah. Yeah. So he's very basically
asant to what are the daughters of Ashtai Aguiz, the king of the meets. Her name
was Kassandani. Apparently he really loved her. And I know you're like, well,
okay, he loved his wife. Well, you know, this was very clearly an arranged marriage.
He was very to his aunt who happens to be the daughter of the King of the Meeds, the
neighboring King, right like.
But he, much later, when spoilers he had conquered Babylon, when she died, he instituted this
ridiculously long period of enforced public mourning on the whole population.
her death.
And this is considered evidence by all the ancient people that like wow, he really loved her,
which was kind of rare for, you know, royal arranged marriages.
Yeah.
So he had two sons with her.
His son, Cambisi's the second who was named after, also named after his grandfather,
who would become the emperor after Cyrus the Great.
And I guess he would be then not only his son, but also his first
cousin. Kind of yes. Yes. We're going to run into somebody here who's their own grandpa. I know it.
And then a second said, Barty, and then three daughters. And I love the names of these three
daughters because the three daughters are named Atosa, are just Stonay and Roxanne.
Rock, say.
Sorry.
Just can't help it.
So like two very person names that that rocks out.
So I mean, which is probably also a very Persian name.
Yeah, but these are not saints.
So no, don't name your kids once again.
Yes.
So, Herodotus, just so the audience knows, I have been pre-sensored on telling this story.
My father, Andrew.
Now we're going to get the expirigated,
bode-larized version of this story.
That's...
Right. If you want the real deal, you'll have to go read some Herodotus.
But so Herodotus has this story about the birth and early childhood of Cyrus the Second.
Cyrus the Great. That is fascinating.
It is wild to say the least.
Yes, okay, so here is the version that father Andrew will allow me to.
tell you. That's right. It's the official censor as the representative of the man. That's right.
That's the the the grand inquisitor as the power in fight the power. Anyway.
So Assygis, King of the Meads, right? His daughter, Mondane,
is about to become Cyrus II.
Cyrus the great's mother as in she's pregnant with him. Okay. This is going to be his grandson.
Cyrus the second. So this is Cyrus's maternal grandfather has a vision
that from his daughter's body, a vision is a dream, right. So he's having a dream. And within
the dream he has a vision that from his daughter's body,
a great flood of water and then grape vines filled with clusters of grapes. So he wakes up.
He is vaguely disturbed by this. It must mean something. So a sari's calls together his
is Magi, is it work?
says, Hey, here's this dream I had. Can you interpret this dream for me?" And he said,
Oh, this is a dream about the sun who is going to come forth from your daughter's body.
The flood represents the fact that he's going to wipe out you and your rule and take your
thrown but then once he does the great vines and the clusters of
rapes represent the fact that it will be successful and prosperous to the kingdom and
bountiful, right?
Once he takes over.
Now, a stiagie's being a bit selfish doesn't like this prospect, right?
He doesn't care about prosperity.
He wants to stay king.
So he calls his main general, military general, Harpagus.
It tells our Pegas look
Take my pregnant daughter, Mondane, you need to take her and you need to end the life of the baby.
So he says that he doesn't have the heart to do this.
To kill this unborn baby. And so he takes her to a bunch of shepherds.
And these shepherds apparently have ways of
the boarding children. And so he gives her to the shepherds to take care of the issue. So
when this happens, the shepherds also don't have the heart to kill this woman's child.
But it so happens that one of the shepherds' wives has a stillborn baby.
Yeah, I mean, a lot of this is kind of similar to the end of his story.
Yes, there's details.
Including the shepherd business and a couple of other things in here.
Um, so she goes and gives her stillborn child to Harpagus, right?
So Z. Look, we took care of the baby and then Shepherd family adopts baby Cyrus when he's born.
So all goes well until Cyrus is like a little kid. He's playing some game with some nobleman's son
and he loses the game to the note.
son and as one does he orders that
novelman son beaten out dare he yes this
causes a big kerfuffle because how
dare some shepherds kid order a nobleman
son be beaten so there's an
investigation and a little trial thing
unfolds and it turns out oh no it turns
out. This is Baby Cyrus.
Now, kid Cyrus, the second, right? He's he's gonna be the king here soon.
The question is did they have the kid beaten? That's resolute. Well, anyway. So,
yeah, apparently his imperiousness was just in the royal bloodline. Like, yes, right, right.
Of him beaten. So, astiogies now finds out, oh dang it, my whole scheme fell apart.
The kid was...
born and now I'm doomed by the fates. So he decides what he needs to do is get revenge on
harpagas for not having taken care of this for him. And so as Diagie calls for harpagas's
first board stun is general's first board son. As Diagie's king of the beads kills
our pack is this first board side and cook them the boils part
parts and he grills parts.
Herodidus doesn't tell us which parts are which.
And then has Big Feast and serves Harpagus his own son.
And then at the end of the dinner, he says, you've been punked.
You're eating your own kid and brings out a tray with his son's head, hands, and feet
To good.
that see it was your son you were eating.
You know, it's it's kind of uncanny how many stories from the pre modern world.
Have that particular element in it.
The I am going to feed you your own kid element.
Yes, never go full Titus and Dronecus folks.
Right. Yes.
Also shows up in the Volsena saga.
Right before a woman lights the entire place on fire.
Yeah.
So
So what's all that story about?
Well, I think Gloria, the origin story of Cyrus II.
Yes.
I think we know.
Now, this is an overly elaborate story, but remember what I said about things getting
exaggerated based on their pressure they have of Cyrus, right?
Yeah.
So with that kind of story in mind, so Cyrus, the second, becomes Cyrus II, and that
he succeeds.
the throne, right? It becomes the king of
Anshin in 559 BC at age 40. And his first order of
business, what he has said to the throne is to go take out his
grandpa, Kigastai Gis and the Medes, and take their
territory. Yeah, that's the first thing he does.
And how does he do this?
Cause we said, you know, the, is the previous kings
didn't really have a good line on expansion, right?
They didn't really have the military power
to go up against the beads.
And they didn't have a lot of other directions to expand.
Well,
Cyrus made a deal with Harpegas, a Stygie's general
who is an actual historical person.
And Harpegas turned on a Stygie's
And took the median army
joined with Cyrus and his Persian army. They got rid of a
Sygees and took media. And he became the king of all media.
Much like myself today. Yes. Sorry, I just heard that
that went out there. I can't count the number of ways you
remind me of Howard Stern.
So he's going to call it now and just yell Bob a booey, Bob
a booey. That's it. Thank you. Thank you.
Or if they weren't before, they will know that I said that.
So that's how it starts.
So I think my theory here, and I don't think this is that far fetched, is that Herodidus
story is essentially a way of trying to explain that.
Yeah.
Why is it that he kills his grandfather?
Well, you know, wipe out his rule and teams up with, with the, yeah, I get what?
Bye.
his top general flip sides on him, but it's not asparagus. It's harpaagus. Yeah.
What is our pagus? Right. Uh, why does his top general flip on him?
I mean, that seems weird. Like normally you don't become somebody's like top
general head of the military. Like if you're a king, that's going to be a guy you
trust a lot.
Cause military coups are a whole thing. Right? Like this guy's the commander of your
You can just...
you at the back and take over kind of any time he wants to. Right. So,
normally this is like your most trusted guy and he flipped out of
Stygues. Yeah. That seems weird. Right. And Cyrus, right, just
decides to white take, kill his grandfather and take his kingdom,
like first order of business after becoming king. That seems a
little odd. Also his father-in-law.
Right. So the whole thing seems a little weird.
Right.
And so I think Herodotus comes up with this story,
probably based on some rumors and things he heard,
and elaborates it out to come up with,
for what kind of reason,
what would generate the kind of animosity toward a stigis,
right, for these two men that leave this?
And certainly if Herodotus' story were true,
That would generate enough adivosity to make the two of them want to kill them right like
I get rid of them
But so regardless of you know the actual reasons that happens
and
so
Cyrus though doesn't stop
Right. So even if it is initial motivation is some kind of revenge for something on us.
he doesn't stop there. They keep rolling. And they roll north west. So he does not immediately
go after the neo-Babalonian empire. Because again, he's now he's got the army of the
needs. He's got his own Persian army, but that's not he's not ready to go up against
the deal Babylonian empire yet. And so he goes north and west across the
top of the fertile crescent and he conquers Lydia and then goes over into Asia Minor, what's
now Turkey, and conquers all of Asia Minor. And the only place where he faces real military
resistance is when he gets to the very western end of Asia Minor, where there are a whole
bunch of Greek city states. So people forget this, that Asia Minor and the First Millennium
NBC is kind of split.
East and West. They're actually a whole bunch of different people groups in Asia Minor. I mean,
aren't the hit tights are from Asia Minor. Right. Right. And in general, in general, now we've talked
about the Greeks being sort of the last ancient Near Eastern culture. But the West end, the very West
end of Asia Minor was pronohelanic in culture, right? That's what Troy is. Yeah, right.
Whereas the eastern portions, like where the hitites were, those sections are very clearly
ancient near eastern and culture.
In the sense that there's cultural curtsy going back and forth with the Louvians and the
hitites and the Hurians, right?
And the Phoenicians and the Syrians, right?
That's their sort of world, right?
and hit that everybody is an Indo-European language as well, which is also correct.
you think about, but it is probably the one, yeah, one of the very oldest that we have
attested. Um, so, but when he hits that resistance, it's at the Greek city states and they sort
of form a league they bond together as Greek city states were want to do when invaded. Uh,
and they was led by a certain king, Cresus, as in riches Cresus. Yes.
a phrase that I know you've all heard, all of you Zoomers, just all the time you're talking about people being rich as Cresus. I know.
When you're soaking like a kille's in his tent, you sit there and think, would that I were rich as Cresus?
But the actual historical creases got wrecked by Cyrus II.
and he adds up to
taking all of Asia Minor. But then he stops. Still doesn't feel like he's ready to go after Babylon.
So he heads back home and then the next set of campaigns, he heads East.
And he makes his way all the way into and makes vassals out of a whole series of cities in the western part of India.
Yeah.
So
He already has this vast swath of land now, right? And if you're the neo-Babaloneans,
you're getting nervous now because you are bordered on the north, on the west, and on
the east by this new Persian Empire. Yeah, which is just again, collot. Yeah. Like,
if you're looking at a map, it's like hanging over them sort of the way West Virginia hangs
over the top of Virginia.
Right West Virginia is the rest of Virginia like looming looming like the sort of Damocles above their heads waiting to drop.
Yeah.
And so in 540 BC, 19 years after he's become king.
So at 19 years he accomplishes all that.
540 BC Cyrus.
feels like, okay, now I'm ready to start making moves against the Neobabelonian Empire.
And so he moves west a little bit from the Iranian Plateau and takes Ilum and Sousa. Sousa
is later going to be the capital of the Persian Empire. So he takes Ilum and Sousa in 540,
but he's got one major obstacle. So if you remember the last episode, we talked about
on how
One of the things Nebuchadnezzar did was he built these border walls.
And we said we didn't know if he made the Lydians and the Meads pay for it.
But he built these border walls. One of those was the median wall,
which was called the median wall, because it was kind of, even though they were technically allies,
remember what we said about that being a little paranoid about being invaded from the west,
or from the east coming west, yeah.
The radio from the east coming away.
into their territory. They put a wall there too that was referred to as the median wall.
And so in order to mount any kind of military attack against the Neobabalone and Empire,
Cyrus had to find a way around the median wall because even with an army that outmatched
the Neobabellonians, which were not totally sure he had them completely outmatched.
in terms of numbers. If they're defending a wall, this isn't going to go well for you.
Right? And so he found a way around it. And that was by... he found the city of Opus, OPIS,
which was a little bit north of Babylon on the Tigris River. There was an afford of the Tigris River.
and if he could forward the river and take it.
Right, he could essentially go through Opus that go around the median wall and then invade sort of the heartland of the neo-Babalonean Empire, the main cities.
And so he marched his army toward Opus, neo-Babalonean army, also marches towards Opus, led by who would become the last neo-Babalonean empire, Navinitis.
The Battle of Opus.
happens in 539 and Navidadis and his Babylonian army get wrecked.
Just obliterated by the Persians.
And we're going to find out some reasons here in a minute.
That's why that may have been.
But once the deal Babylonian army is routed at Opus, Cyrus and his Persian army marched south.
South, they marching to Sipar. Remember that city.
that we talked about last time, March of the SIPR and took it without resistance. On October
10th, 539 BC. Hey, that's right, kids. Tomorrow is the 2,564th anniversary of Cyrus Marching
into SIPR. You're going to do anything special for the holiday or?
Well, there's a bigger one. There's a bigger one.
Because then on October 12th, which will be Sunday, this Sunday will be the
2,564th anniversary of this, he marched into Babylon.
So Sunday, 2,564th anniversary of Cyrus taking the city of Babylon.
Um, March to the Babylon, it took Babylon with no resistance.
Which strongly suggests that the Babylonians are like, yeah.
lol
Come on, Navaditis Stunk.
Yeah.
He was bad.
There were a series of weak bad emperors, as we mentioned last time after
Nebuchadnezzar, right?
In fairly quick succession.
Navaditis was one of them didn't have, and this is probably why they got
routed so badly.
He probably didn't have the confidence and loyalty of his troops.
Um, because we're we say no resistance, right?
This means that Navaditis was trying to rally more troops and couldn't get
any.
And like the nobles and the priests and stuff in these cities were just like hi Cyrus how you doing we look forward to your leadership?
Right so yeah this.
Like how bad do you have to be?
I guess.
Ruler when your own people are just like whoo glad that's over who's the new guy you know.
So...
But we have, we have an inscription.
We have an inscription from this event,
2,564 years ago Sunday,
where Cyrus left a little cylinder inscription.
And this is a tiny cylinder.
You hear cylinder inscription.
You think it's going to be some big standing monument.
These cylinders are tiny.
Like a size of a hand or a figure.
A third.
the size of a highlighter. Wow. That's with tiny inscriptions on them. They are very small.
But so there is a cylinder that was found called the Cyrus cylinder in a fit of creativity.
That was found in the in the depths of in the bottom of the Esseguila. Remember that from last time?
the main temple of Marduk.
in Babylon, like the ancient temple,
they already thousands of year old years old
at this point, Temple of Marduk,
at the center of Babylon.
We find this cylinder from this date
when he took Babylon in which proclaimed Cyrus,
or Cyrus is proclaiming himself,
but he probably didn't write it himself.
The king of Babylon, the king of Sumer and Akad,
and the king of the four corners of the world,
And then just a ton of smack talk about Nabinitis.
Now and how happy everyone was that he came and took over, including the God Marduk.
Yeah, was just super happy to greet Cyrus. Nice.
I'd get rid of that Navi-Nightis cloud. Like you got to feel a little bad for the guy.
like, yeah.
Yeah.
You just found out one day that he had no friends, right?
Like no one liked him.
Um.
Do you want to be liked by Marduk?
I'm just, I guess you kind of want to, but...
Well, I mean, just it would be nice if Nabilidas felt
like somebody was still as pal.
Right.
Like, there's somebody who felt bad
about him not being emperor anymore, you know?
Yeah.
And it's not like Cyrus has this long record
as an emperor, right?
Like, they're basically favoring an unknown quantity
over him.
Yeah.
You know, that's got a sting.
That's all I'm saying, right?
But how is that empathy?
Father Stephen, I've never I have I have sympathy for Nabilitis. Oh wow. Wow. Uh, okay.
Do we know that do we know that it just it just seems it seems tough man. It seems tough. You know. Um,
I mean, if if if God forbid, I was transferred to another parish,
and with the new guy showed up, like just everyone in the parish was like, we don't know who you are,
but we're so glad you're here. That would be
That'd be a kick of the teeth, you know, you'd feel a little bad.
Uh-huh.
That's been known to happen once in a while.
Yeah, but it'd be a little rough.
It'd be a little rough.
Yes.
Um, but so not too long after this, right?
This happens at 539, October 12, 539 in 530 BC Cyrus dies.
Um, and he dies doing what he loved.
He's in battle conquering stuff. So there you go.
Went out with his boots on.
We're not sure exactly the exact spot where he was when he died.
We know that this group of people called the Masagate,
who lived somewhere in what is modern day Kazakstan and Uzbekistan.
And they may have been kind of nomadic, right? They may not have been...
settled in one kind, in one sense, is a set there in that region.
Central Asia. Yeah.
Either revolted against Persian rule or attacked Persian territory, it's
unclear. It's partially unclear because we don't know just how much
control Cyrus had at that point, that deep into Asia. Right. Because
this is around what would have been the border. Right. This is
around the limits of his...
control. So are these people who are technically in lands he controlled who are revolting or
are these people from just outside who are moving in? It's not totally clear. Right. But he goes to
fight them and he fights them. The exercise is to say at the headwaters of the Sardarria river,
we know it wasn't the literal headwaters of the Sardarria river because that's way to
to deep in Asia.
But the word that translates.
headwaters could just mean upriver basically. So would they say upriver like how far upriver?
We don't know, but it's somewhere around the Sir Dario River, which flows through that part of Asia,
for miles. But somewhere in there, in battle against the Masagate, he's killed.
And his body is brought back to Pasar Gide, right, which is...
the city over which
Accompanied he's was king, right?
Sort of the Accompanied city.
And he's put into a limestone tomb
that is still there to this day.
Yeah, which is crazy.
That's I don't necessarily recommend
taking a vacation vacation in Iran right now.
What if you were to you could go
see yeah and and you know,
Kids if you wanna look up but...
This looks like this limestone tomb.
There is in fact a Wikipedia article.
It's called like the tomb of Cyrus or
tomb of Cyrus who wears something like that as a photo.
So yeah, that tomb is still there.
Now, herodotus, this inscription is not still there,
but herodotus again tells us that there used to be
an inscription on it that said,
roughly I am Cyrus, I conquered the four quarters
of the world, do not begrudge me this small piece
of land for my burial.
I mean
reasonable. A reasonable request. Yeah. So, and we also know that when when he
conquered Persia, Alexander the Great spent a bunch of time there at the
tomb. Hmm.
Probably trying to do some pagan equivalent of grave soaking. Yeah,
as he says, he's gonna soak up as anointing or whatever. Yeah.
Yeah.
I know you see your telegraphing the third...
or in half, that's what you do with the Cyrus is anointing.
Welcome.
So sort of some last notes here as we draw the first half to a close.
It's important to note some of the differences between the Persian Empire and pre-seating
and even a lot of succeeding empires.
So one of those is...
the fact that so there's there's a series of tensions right so one of these is
that Cyrus unlike all previous empires and pretty much all later empires
frankly does not try to impose Persian culture as a hegemonic culture upon his
Yeah, he does the opposite.
Yeah, like you worship those gods keep doing that. That's cool. Or even you know, you've got a local
Marantown Council or governors, whatever. That's cool. Just run things. Make sure you send some tax money.
Yeah. So he allows every region to continue to practice its own no-mose. It's current no-mose.
As long as they acknowledge him and pay tribute and in terms of their religion, he lets them practice
just their religion. He just says, hey, whatever God
you worship offers some sacrifice.
to him or her for me. Yeah, as the emperor. Well, as do what you like, right? Weirdly tolerant for the ancient
word. Yes. And this is, this is, yeah, this is unheard of, right? This is unheard of. We saw the
Syrians certainly worked this way. Validins out this way. Greeks aren't going to be this way. They're
They're going to try to hellenize everything.
Romans aren't this way, right?
That's...
So this is a very different, almost cosmopolitan approach to what he's doing.
And it's part of the success of the Persian Empire.
Right. When you do that, turns out you get less revolts.
Right. Because everybody's kind of allowed to do their own thing.
Yeah. Right. As long as they, as long as they sort of acknowledge your
your authority. And this is part of why we don't get that much literature in the
Old Testament from the Persian period. The fifth century BC, the 400s BC, is
pretty peaceful in Judea.
Huh, the kind of, do some people just kind of allow to do their thing for 100 years.
Right? There's no one really bothering them there. Right? You talk about the Esther stuff.
That's mostly in Persia and in Babylon, the Babylonian just, but it's pretty peaceful.
Right? It's not until the Greeks come and the Greeks then try to Hellenize the culture that you
get them, that can be in revolt and yeah, everything we find out about in those, those Christian
Testament text, but Persian Empire is pretty peaceful, right? Now that said...
They also introduced though a common language
which is not
Persian which is not Persian. Yeah, not Persian not Persian
So they have a language to facilitate trade and everything yeah and the administration of the empire
But they don't impose their own. It's actually Aramaic Aramaic and if you want to know the story of exactly how that
Weirdness came to be there's a great book called empires of the word
By
Nicholas Osler, I think it is. And what he says in that book is actually is that
the kind of native airmanic speakers are these nomadic traders, mercantile types,
and they keep kind of getting pushed around the empire. And because they keep getting pushed around,
everyone, everywhere wants to do business with them. And so they learn their language.
And before you know it, it's to be very, very anachronistic about it. The lingual franca of the
as a person empire.
And so that's the official language of the court is not Persian, but Aramaic, this
Semitic language belonging to these wandering businessmen.
It's wild. It's a cool story. Yeah. And Aramaic persists in the East. That's why people are still
speaking Aramaic in the New Testament period in Judea and Galen. Yeah, it's a marriage.
to the Persians, right? But it continues further east than that. So the Persian Empire.
long gone at this point, right? But they're still speaking Aramaic in what's now Pakistan.
That's crazy. Right? That's why St. Thomas could go there. There are ancient churches and stuff
in Pakistan with inscriptions in Aramaic. Right? So yeah, Aramaic was a lingua franca before
Greek was right yeah yeah um so there's that uh
And we also get interestingly. Now, obviously, the Persian Empire, there's not a separation of church and state, but
You get the first inkling of some kind of concept like that in the sense that in the sense that
As we mentioned there is no attempt to impose Persian religion and
So to understand how significant this is we have to compare it again, right?
So when the new Babylonian Empire rises to prominence.
They take that to mean Marduk is now the supreme God in the world.
Yeah.
Because he's the God of the Babylonians and Babylon rules the world.
Right.
And all other gods are either assimilated into the Babylonian religion or demoted into the side of it.
But everything, the religion of everyone within the Babylonian Empire is expected to be redone to fit.
Right. And that's why you have the
happen that happen in Daniel like people getting thrown in furnaces.
Right.
This kind of thing because they will refuse to accommodate the Jewish people
refuse to count it babbling religion.
That kind of thing happens again with the Greeks as we mentioned in
the bag of these.
That doesn't happen with the Persians.
It's wild.
Right.
So there's something fundamentally different there in terms of religion.
That leads us into when we come back in our second half.
going to discuss.
Persian religion.
All right, well, on that cliffhanger,
we're gonna take our first break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Poised between east and west, between Orthodox and Catholic, with the wania, the last of Europe's pagan nations, did not forget its ancient tales such as that of the giant-tests-neringa, egg-lay-queen of serpents, and the iron wolf.
Rather, they fulfilled and enriched them with legends like the hill of crosses and the miracle-working icon of our Lady of the Gate of the Dawn.
in the world.
and the cross. Father Andrew Stephen Damack and Deacon Seraphim Richard Rowland take a very
personal pilgrimage into a land where history and legend have met and fused. Where Orthodox
Christians have lived as a minority for nearly seven centuries. Their faith founded upon
the blood of martyrs and the witness of dozens of saints. To find this book and others
like it you can go to store.inchantfaith.com.
Again, that is store
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen De Young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
And we're back.
So, Father Stephen, did you get a copy of my new book that I co-wrote with?
You
can say from Richard Rollins?
You did not give me such a book.
Oh, well, you didn't give me one of yours either.
And the despite the stirring
introduction I gave to Deacon Cherubim, if that is real name,
he did not give me a copy on it.
Well, what can I say?
that
we are back and we're gonna be talking now about
Persian religion, probably if people know anything about Persian religion, they know about
Zoroastrianism or at least the name. And so they might assume that Cyrus was a Zoroastrian.
And then maybe that's why he was so tolerant of other religions. Is that true? What's
that all about?
I'm once again disappointed in the lack of calls.
Well, you know, it's I don't know people are maybe they're just listening so
closely that they just don't have anything to say.
They gotta have some Cyrus related questions.
Come on, man.
Some kurociosity is.
Thank you, thank you.
We'll see.
I'll keep my eyes peeled.
So, like I said, you can lie to Mike about what you're gonna ask.
Just, you know, call it ask whenever.
I don't recommend.
They'll communicate with us.
We have someone at...
actually in the YouTube chat who is going by the moniker of Christoph
for us the verangian who writes, man oh man, been waiting for
discussion from you find Jens on zero asianism. So I guess this
is his moment. Okay, this is yes.
Woo, okay. So yeah, thank you for that. Woo. So a little
What, whoo on this film?
What was Cyrus a zero-astrian maybe?
Yeah, we don't super know the answer is maybe. So there's a number of parts to this
right in terms of even assessing this question. So zero-astrian is internally
claims to go back to the Bronze Age. It's a little dubious. It's a little dubious. The Zoroastrianism
as such. Now, there are probably religious traditions contained within Zoroastrianism that do,
as we're going to see when we get into the meat here, talking about Zoroastrianism and its origins,
It is a sort of revision or
reformation.
of much older, basically pagan religious forms.
Yeah, the idea that what exists now
is the same thing under that name
that has always existed for 2,500, 3,000 years or whatever.
That's just not true.
Right.
But the roots of what is being practiced now
certainly do extend this far back.
Right. And so...
So the place where we first have records of Zoroastrian religion is the 6th century
BC, which may sound familiar because that's when Cyrus lived.
Yeah.
So it's contemporaneous with Cyrus.
The favorite of him maybe being Zoroastrian is the fact that we have the names of
some of his advisors and stuff.
And some of those names are potentially related
to Zoroastrianism.
Yeah, rather than like usual pagan Theophorex.
Yeah, and you notice I'm being vague because
even when you say that, it's like,
when does the term for fire become a technical term?
Yeah.
Right?
What is it to Zoroastrian technical term?
But what does it just mean fire?
You know what I'm like?
So it's easier with the theophoric, it's easier to demonstrate.
But as we're going to see, zero-astrophism is not really going to have theophoric in the true sense.
It's going to deal more with concepts.
And so it's hard to know whether, okay, this word or concept is included in somebody's name.
Does it carry within their name the specific?
specifically Zoroastrian religious relevance.
Hard to know at this point.
Against him being a Zoroastrian is, as we mentioned,
his weird for the time views of religious tolerance.
Because Zoroastrianism was not that.
As we mentioned and was we're going to talk about now.
and its origins, Zoroastrianism was a reform movement of previous paganism. And so it was not particularly
tolerant of old-style paganism. Yeah, it seems to be, I mean, is it correct to say that it seems to be
like some of this kind of acceilage, philosophizing, you know, yeah, yeah,
formalizing kind of thing that's going...
elsewhere in the world. Right, right, that it represents a sort of elevated version of
Iranian, which is ultimately Indian Hindu meaning paganism in a different way than like Brahminism
or Buddhism, but still essentially doing the same thing.
Yeah.
And...
Although even comparing it to Brahminism in some ways, it's going to be a rebellion against a kind of Brahminism.
But so because of that, because it self-consciously exists as a rejection of certain other religious practices,
the idea that it would sort of then tolerate those religious practices in an imperial setting seems weird.
Yeah, it's also true that Cyrus did
not make Zoroastrianism or any other religion, the religion of the Persian Empire that he
found it. It's his successors who made Zoroastrianism the official religion. That said, the
idea that okay, we have an empire we need to make up our religion, that doesn't happen.
Yeah, that dog don't hurt.
So that's not a possibility either.
So it's not like Cyrus didn't know anything about zero-astridism and then his successors
just invented this religion and rolled it out.
That's a work either.
Zero-astridism, the most likely explanation is that this is a religious tradition, probably
a minority religious tradition over against the sort of general run of the mill.
Iranian paganism that already existed and had existed for some period of time, we can't
know exactly how long before Cyrus, Cyrus is aware of it, but it only becomes ascendant
and the official religion under his successors.
Yeah, it makes sense that he would not be a practitioner of it because it's as you said,
it's an intolerant religion.
Right.
Cyrus, I think the most likely explanation for his general religious, weirdly religiously
tolerant attitude, his seeming lack of concern for establishing any kind of religious base
for his newly established empire, right, etc. May just be that Cyrus wasn't all that pious.
Yeah. Just wasn't that I mean, he just wasn't a very religious guy.
That's that's
stuff didn't resonate with him so much. And so he didn't have a problem. Obviously he's
not an atheist or something who wants to abolish religion, but he's just sort of doesn't care
about it that much. So he just kind of lets people do whatever they want in that regard
and considers it all good. I think that's the easiest and most likely explanation.
So, uh...
Zoroastrianism gets its name, and that name being the Hellenization of its name, from
Zoroaster, which is the Hellenization of the name of the Prophet of Zoroastrianism,
Zerathustra.
Zoroathustra.
Something like that.
I'm going with Nietzsche.
Anyway, I don't know how to pronounce Persian.
I don't know about that.
So, Zerathustra is this.
prophetic figure who is going to be basically a reformer against the previously existing
Iranian religion. Sort of parallel again, sort of similar to the Buddha in regard to
Hinduism. So that's obviously since that's Hellenized.
That's not what Zoroastrian's called themselves.
The Zoroastrian name for Zoroastrianism is Mazda Yazna, which Yazna is the word for
worship.
It really means the worship of Mazda.
Not the car manufacturer.
Right.
D.E.
Nobody worships Mazda's.
Um, to be like worshiping a Hugo.
Sorry, sir.
Wow.
All the me.
So it's all the me.
I own yours out there really, really scraping at the moment.
They were such a big deal like in the year like 2000.
The Mazda me.
I like the convertibles like that.
You know, our, our, uh, years ago, our mutual friend Michael
Lenzman, when I met him, he was driving a, uh, a Mazda me.
That totally checks out.
Gave it up.
Yes, that so checks out gave it up when he got married.
That would have been what like 2000 what seven?
No, no, it hasn't been that long.
It hasn't been that long actually, but yeah, okay.
But yeah, that's yeah.
I won't go any further out of respect to the man of lands.
But so the other term that zero
Astero Astrians used for
their own religion is bedin, which means the good religion, which is the good religion over
against paganism. Right. Right. So this is what we're talking about a minute ago. And so
preseroastriism, like the or level of Persian religion is basically Vedic religion.
So it's Hinduism as you find it.
in the Vedas. Right. So V, V related, remember religion is not a separate thing from culture and
everything. So there was also apparently a very rigid cast system in Persian culture before
arthostor. And the highest cast was the cast of the priests and according to these
oral aspirin story.
So, that sounds pretty good.
Either you could do a play-doh, put the philosopher king's preaching. Yeah, I don't want to be
a priest-king. You can go ahead with that.
No, no, no.
get over there.
Just, yes.
I know it's so funny.
People scream about theocracy.
I'm like, no, that's a bad idea.
It's a bad idea.
Build your cigarettes.
Anyway, so yeah, the highest cast were the, were this priestly class.
And they were guilty of two primary crimes in oppressing the lower classes.
The first was they demanded what were apparently exorbitant numbers of A.
animal sacrifices. So they're basically plundering all the wealth of the people, the poorer people,
by demanding all of their animals for sacrifices, and of course the priests are eating the meat
of the sacrifices. Right. Right. This is a way of talking about greed. Right. They're exploiting their
religious position. Basically both of these are going to revolve around. They had this monopoly
on access to the gods and religion, and therefore, and they exploited that for their own benefit.
So
One way was plundering their wealth through animal sacrifices.
And the second thing was they controlled all the Homa plants.
Wow.
Which these plants had a derived hallucinogen.
I mean, I feel like I read that was used.
That was used for spiritual visions.
And they were the only ones who had access to it.
Which meant they were the only ones who could access the spiritual world.
And these visions because only they have
the plants. It's like a Frank Herbert novel. Yes, or like another novel as you pointed out.
Yes, that's right. Yes, actually, it's true. Yes, I should look at my own notes in front of me here.
Yeah, Homa, I mean, you write all these things out and then you don't even look at them.
Well, you know, it's really tempting to just kind of take a nap while you monologue, but
but now so, so how much it
that this word which refers to this sort of hallucinogenic drink or whatever they ingest it,
that the word is cognate with the Vedic Sanskrit word, soma, which is not related to the Greek soma,
meaning body. But soma for those who are Aldous Huxley readers, I won't say fans. I don't know.
I don't know if you read Brave New World, you know that the happy
drug that everybody's taken in there that keeps everybody, you know,
docile is called summa. So so yes, yes, I mean, there's all kinds of weird,
weird stuff going on in here. But yeah, I mean, it's like this kind of like they
control the plant that gives you visions, right? That could the connection to the
divine and so forth. Like the spice must flow, but only for the navigators of the
starships kind of thing. Yes, they so they've got this sort of chokehold on all the
means of accessing the device.
and they're exploiting it. And so Zarathustra comes along to end that. Right. And so he's going to reform
religion on a number of levels. So one of those is going to be the attacking the first problem,
which is the sacrificial system to the Vedic gods. They're demanding all these sacrifices for all
all these different gods.
And over against that, right, over against those Vedic gods, like you can say the Rig Veda,
which are basically parallel to Hindu gods.
He's going to talk about, so there are a couple of words that already exist for gods.
As we've talked about, most languages, especially most Indo-European languages, have two different
words that can be used for gods.
One that means like higher tier gods and what that means like lower tier gods and spirits.
We've talked about this before.
Yeah.
Right.
So Latin has this, Greek has this, right?
And so does old Persian.
And so there is a word, a hurrah, derived from a surah, that means God, but that's a higher
tier God.
And we can see there's another word for sort of lower tier gods in spirit.
But Zerathustra is going to talk about Ahura Mazda, so which means the God Mazda.
As we said, there were religious, called the worship of Mazda.
So this Mazda, not a Miata, this God pretty clearly in the way this God is described,
is sort of taking the Vedic gods, Mitra and Faruna and smushing them together.
Right, the way they're talked about like in the Rig Veda.
You take the two of them, you kind of roll them into one and you get something like Mazda,
like a Hurrah Mazda. And so a Hurrah Mazda is basically the divine embodiment of all the good stuff.
He creates the whole universe out of light.
And he's the one responsible for maintaining justice. And this is a concept of justice.
So for-
for the Persians, it's called Asha, right?
But we've talked about this in different cultures,
like in Egypt, it's Ma'at, Mishpah in Hebrew, right?
This idea of cosmic order, where everything is in its place
and doing its thing and functioning properly,
that sort of order of justice.
They have that same concept.
It's a hurrah mazda who created everything out of light
originally and who then maintains that justice.
Now, if you...
We've read a little bit or heard a little bit about zero-astrianism.
You've been misinformed probably on this point.
Because you've probably, if you've gotten the super brief summary of zero-astrianism,
you've been told, oh, it's a dualistic religion.
And specifically that there's like a good God in the evil God.
that.
it. They just have two gods, a good one and an evil one. That is not true about zero
asterionism. That is more true, not totally true, but more true about manicionism.
Yeah, which is a much later development. Much later thing. Manicionism isn't eastern,
like far eastern, like Persian and Chinese and Central Asian,
primarily, although it went into...
Europe and even Western Europe and Africa, a form of narcissism that is sort of a blending of
narcissism and zero-astrianism in the post-Christian period. And Manichianism does have it like a good
god in an evil god. Zoroastrianism doesn't really. So the quote-unquote evil god
The people talk about is the Anger of Manu, not the A-
degree menu, Angra menu, which is a
heramazda's shadow. And the reason
it's described as a heramazda's shadow
is precisely because they don't want
to say it's a separate being.
That is like co-equal with with a
heramazda. Yeah. Angra menu is his shadow.
So if you have light, that light sort of...
cash shadows, right? It's like necessitated by, right? Don't go too young on this either.
I know there's some of you Peterson heads out there who are already trying to do this whole car all young and brace your shadow thing. It's not that either.
It's not that either.
But it is essentially the answer to, well, hey, if a hero of osd is all the good stuff,
where does all the bad stuff come?
And the bad stuff is the stuff that lies in his shadow is the idea. Right. You don't even want to over personify his shadow. Right. But nor is it just, oh, he has negative qualities too.
Right. It's sort of a thing that's kept separated, but not a separate being.
Yeah.
Now that said, the other right...
that Mithra and Virutika get shoved together into Hormazda.
The other Vedic gods don't totally get done away with.
The old pagan gods.
They are just, oh, those are fictional.
We're done with those.
There's already a Persian word, Yazada, that was used for lesser gods and like nature
spirits and stuff.
sort of maybe yeah we're like demonis in Greek
And so they get those old vane gods and stuff get demoted right to to this status.
Okay. Now, there's sort of phases and how they're talked about within Zoroastrianism.
So it seems pretty clear that in the earlier phases, in the most ancient phases, they
weren't really seen as separate beings from a heramasta. They were seen as being some kind of powers
or emanations from a heramasta.
Yeah. What we would call energies of a heramasta or something. They take those things that
It used to be worshiped as gods that were independent and it-
and make them just kind of functions or powers or attributes or elements of a
hermastah. Sort of depersonified. Yeah. So so related to that before we move to
the next section in our notes, we actually have a call that's come in father.
Can you believe it? Is it a Zoroastrian? I don't know. I don't know. I don't know.
is this religion is not identified on the call board okay but we we do have
Dan calling from Ontario, California.
All right.
So I and Dan, welcome to the Lord of Spirit's podcast.
Apparently you're from Father Stevens old stomping grounds.
Yes, I am.
How are you guys doing today?
Good. How are you?
Is the mills mall still there?
Yes, actually, I live pretty darn close to it.
Okay. Wow. Wow.
You know, there's an Ontario in my background as well.
There's Ontario Ohio, which is right near where I went to high school.
So, so we found something strange that we haven't common fathers to even.
All right, Dan, are you a Zoroastrian calling in to correct fathers to even all these ridiculous things he just said?
You know, in all honesty, I'm not sure if I am and that's part of my question.
Okay.
I mean, you would know if wouldn't you know if you'd been initiated into fire worship?
I feel like your nose is...
Is this like a Vatican II anonymous Christians thing?
Are there anonymous zero Astrians?
I don't know.
So as a five day thing,
I decided to go to a orthodox year
and have a conversation with priest there.
And he called me a pagan.
So now I'm very curious as to what is the actual definition
of a pagan?
And it is...
I'm pretty sure it's not people again, goodness and normal.
I don't know.
The Virgin Virgin Connie Swale would say otherwise.
I am sure I'm picking up what you are laying down.
Nice.
Yes.
I mean, I don't, I don't know what this priest exactly had on his mind.
There is other than his hat.
Yeah, I mean, so like the, you know, the Latter-day Saints, I mean, there's a certain level on which
that religion is similar to ancient paganism, a certain level, right? Because there's multiple
gods that can theoretically be worshiped. But when, when we talk about paganism on this show,
We're not referring to Mormonism.
but referring rather to the religion's practice
where initially there are kind of regional gods,
and then eventually you start getting Imperial pantheons
collected together, but the idea is that there are
disembodied spirits that are particularly worshiped
through embodiment in idols,
and the worship is conducted primarily
through offering food sacrifices to those idols.
And then, you know, to use that to kind of manipulate the God and get what it is that you want out of them.
And the reason why paganism is called paganism, where the word came from, is it originally basically means...
It's from Greek and what it essentially means is hillbillies.
uh, pago, meaning hill. Um, and the reason why that term is used that way is because it's the
It comes about, if I remember correctly, it comes about in the Christian period, the idea
as well, the people in the cities are much more Christians, but the people kind of out
in the countryside, they're still practicing this older, idolatrous religion.
And so they just basically called them the hillbillies, effectively, really.
So yeah, so that's what mean by paganism.
I think that, as I said, I think that what Mormonism has in common with paganism is the idea
that there are multiple gods that can be worshipped.
to win that.
is not the only thing that constitutes actual paganism. So I mean, I wouldn't say to you as
a, you know, a member of the, I assume you're part of the Utah group, right? The Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. Yeah, not the fundamentals. Yeah, I mean, there's, you know,
there's dozens and dozens of LDS groups, but you're part of the big one. Yeah, I wouldn't,
I wouldn't say you're a pagan. I mean, I would, you know, I would say you are LDS, or you're, I mean,
I mean, I know that Mormon is...
I mean, maybe under your new profit president, as it comes in,
Mormon will come back as a word you guys are allowed to use for yourself. I don't know, but
but that's what I would say. I would talk about your particular thing. But yeah, I mean paganism is
is like I said, it's this, it's a very broad term refers to a lot of different religious traditions,
but they tend to all have this in common. There's idolatry at the center. You know, the use of
the use of images to trap and control spirits and offering sacrifices to those images
in order to have this.
relationship with the God. So I know that's my kind of short somewhat
Randley version of what paganism is. Is there anything you might add to that
father, Steven?
Well, I mean, when we we use it on the show, we're usually talking about
Yeah, religion religions that involve the sacrificial worship of
of
God's slash goddesses, usually involving
that's what we mean by by paganism. And that's why we say there's sort of in the ancient world sort of all you have is paganism. I agree with father Andrew. He probably meant more like polytheist.
you know, which you could argue that all these various ways is polyphistic. Not just because there's a heavenly father and a heavenly mother, but because there are in existence multiple heavenly fathers.
and heavenly mothers. That is polyphistic. The church fathers sometimes use the term polyphistic.
We very rarely use the term pagan. They usually just talk about the Greeks. Even the ones who
were Greek and are writing in Greek refer to what we would call pagans as the Greeks. So I think
I think we should go back to that and just make all the Greek Orthodox people mad.
Yeah, it's clear of the
taken part, but I'm not quite sure what you mean about how LDS worship
multiple God that something I've never been taught.
Well, I mean, so my understanding, correct me if I'm wrong here,
is that, you know, the people on earth all have all shared
the same thoughts on the way.
I mean, I'm not sure what you mean about how LDS worship,
is that the people on Earth all have all share.
one Heavenly Father and Heavenly Mother. And you had worshiped the Heavenly Father. But there
are potential multiple Heavenly Fathers that could be worshiped. But it's sort of well you have
your local one, but there's a potentially infinite number. So that's where the polytheism aspect
of it comes into play. It's not so much that, according to my understanding, that the LDS
I can't just worship of all those beings,
but that they are all worshipful
and in other contexts they certainly could be
and maybe have been worshiped.
So is that not so?
I mean, I understand the possibility of,
you know, other heavenly fathers.
Yeah.
Okay, but for, but I've never heard of anybody
who should be any of it.
someone just did the one of this.
or all these things.
So yeah, I mean,
of right, but that's what that's understand.
That's not required for polytheism.
So like they should, they should actual pagans,
who we call polytheists, didn't worship all the gods.
Yeah, they just mainly worship.
They just worshiped one or two, right?
The gods of their city, right?
Or their area where they were,
the place where they were,
they worshiped those one or two,
at an acknowledged existence of.
Well, yeah, those folks over there have theirs and they have theirs.
So, more menism would be like that or letters as it would be like that, but just on an intergalactic scale rather than on a local scale.
We're not talking about the next city, we're talking about another planet.
Yeah, yeah.
All righty. Well, thank you very much for calling Dan.
Okay, well rolling on one final bit in this half of the Lord of Spirit.
Not a Zoroastrian.
Whatever else our friend may be.
He's not a Zoroastrian.
So yeah, so we're going to talk about some specific practices.
I wanted to say before that, I wasn't quite done.
With the, we were talking about the old Vedic gods, right?
Get a kind of promoted.
And it was long causes that throw me, Father.
in the early-
the earliest phases, well that's why they get edited out, I guess. I mean, I could, so
the early phases are saying they're kind of seen, they're turned into sort of emanations
or qualities or aspects of a heramazda. But they're still talked about, I mean, they have
personal names. They're still kind of talked about in language, not that dissimilar from
the way they were talked about it.
the Vedas until you get to, especially the Muslim period, right? So the second person empire
that we mentioned before, the Susannids, get invaded in that empire and get swiped out
by Arab Muslim armies. And so in order to try to keep functioning under Islamic rule, because
if there's one thing Islam doesn't like it.
idolatrous paganism. If it's two things they don't like it's that. Well okay I would
not say it was about to say. Even I pulled back from that anyway. So they shift to
saying okay well those those Vedic gods now they're like angels. Yeah so there's
It's kind of a shift to put it into terms.
more amenable to the Muslim, right? So that, right? So they're trying to cast
sort of cast themselves as monotheists, right? No, we just worshiped the one
God of Herbados, I see. We're monotheists. And these other beings we talk about
are just they're like angels, right? Like you guys got angels? Yeah, right? So
yeah, see they're like angels. But that seems to be a sort of not the original
There seems to be a lot more care.
over of their old divine status in the original concept. But you can also see in that idea of
there being this multitude of emanations of a hermastah. You can see how, and it's some of
the other things we've said, you could probably see some connection points already to nosticism
that it'll explain how Manicannism ends up coming to exist later on.
Yeah.
places where they link together. So then in terms of religion in terms of religious practice, like
what were Zoroastrian's doing when we first meet them back in the 6th century BC
in the original Persian Empire. So essentially the religion as such, the religious practices as such
are aimed at a kind of what we would call spiritual warfare.
So you're doing certain rituals.
and saying mantras which very clearly is related to mantras five times a day, in order to help preserve the order of the cosmos that we are talking about, the order of justice that's put into the world originally by
by her son, the Asha and to sort of perpetuate
keep the world going. So you have the series of rituals. You have these
mantras that are pronounced five times a day and you're a part of this. And then
you've got our friend, how much coming back? You have the use of psychedelics
that are the spirit world now liberated from just that Brahmin class, from that
that priestly cast so that everyone could use it.
Such that the
So water is important in Zoroastrian ritual at this point.
And so there is a thing, there's an initiation ritual, which involves water, and it involves you going into the water.
So clearly, that's where we stole baptism, and has nothing to do with Jewish ritual washings or any of the ritual washings.
the ritual washing.
for making you a religion, clearly just stolen from the versions. But you go to the water and then
key element, you take home after the first time and you have your first trip.
Your first psychedelic trip, that's what initiates you sort of into the religion.
That's what makes you that part of able to participate in these ritual processes that
perpetuate the order of the world.
And so there's sort of an annual cycle of festivals in addition to the daily
mantras and the rituals.
There are fires that are tended in the old,
so in the old Persian Empire there were three primary fires in three different cities
that were said to by burning
keep the world going.
Yeah, and I think and there's
this idea that the fires go back to a fire initially lit by Zara Thrustra himself.
And actually, you know, a number of years ago, I was in Toronto doing a speaking engagement.
And a friend of mine was taking me around the city.
And he said, oh, hey, there's a, there's actually a party community here in Toronto.
So if you don't know, folks, parcys are a group of zero astrians.
who at some point a long time ago immigrated from Iran to India. And so there are Indians
or Austrians. And there's not a lot of them. There's not a lot of them in the world.
There's not a lot of Zoroastrians in the world, honestly. And they have a community up
there. And so there's a Zoroastrian community center and temple there. And so we pulled
off, and I'm always kind of religious, I'm curious. And so we came upon this young lady
who was sitting down and reading on a...
a bench and she asked us who we were, she could tell that we weren't part of her group.
And we said, Hey, we're just curious.
We want to know what it is that y'all do.
And so she took us on a tour and it was kind of a big sort of mansion and mostly essentially
a community center, but they did have a room that was dedicated to their religious rituals.
And she said, you know, this is our, I think she might have said temple over here.
I said, but you can't, you can't go in there.
You can't step your foot in there.
And so he said, okay, that's cool.
But I said to her,
you know, if I don't,
if I was long as I don't go in there,
if I don't put my foot in there,
can I like peek my head in the door?
Can I look around, look, look inside
so I could see what's in there
cause the door was open.
And she said, yeah, that's okay.
And so I poked my head in the door
and it was, you know, rectangular room,
not very ornate.
And then on one end of it was sort of a raised platform.
And in the middle of that platform was what looked like
one of our infant baptismal fonts,
you know, so like a big sort of kettle.
And in it was a pile of ashes.
It was not burning at that moment,
but the idea I think is that, you know,
wherever you go in the world,
if you go to Zoraaster and Temple
and they've got their fire there,
that it has.
as this connection, sort of like, you know, almost like apostolic succession or whatever,
you know, that it goes all the way back to that original fire lit by their founding
prophet himself.
Because those three from the old Persian Empire are all out.
But right.
Yeah.
Supposedly ashes from them have continued burning, right.
Right.
It all places.
Yes.
Yeah.
And so the other famous thing potentially.
if anything is famous about zero asterionism is their quote unquote burials, which aren't
really burials.
Yeah.
Which sort of fly in the face of what every pagan in the world did with the dead.
That's in that they actually would expose the bodies in an elevated place so that they
would be eaten by birds.
All the other pages of the ancient world.
were desperately trying to stop that from happening.
Like that was the igdeminius curse of death that no one wanted.
But right, that's how they buried that.
Yeah, I mean, you know, featured in the Iliad don't leave the bodies out to be eaten by animals.
But so they would. And the idea was that because everything is created out of light,
that includes people. The light is in some way at M
of a hermastah himself. And so by your body being devoured that releases the light that's trapped within you to return to.
Yeah, to their God. And again, you can see how narcissism dovetails into that. But you can also see shades of Brahminism in that.
and other sort of traditions, right?
So this isn't, Zerastrianism is not
this completely foreign thing that shows up.
Yeah, but it is also its own unique sort of evolution and twist on these various traditions. Yeah, yeah, yeah, that you find elsewhere.
As we also mentioned, very intolerant religion.
Unlike Cyrus's policies, this would especially become apparent in the Sassanate Empire, which as we mentioned is post Christian.
But
Absolutely brutal persecutors of Christians within the Persian Empire, like well beyond even the stuff the Roman stead to Christians.
And you can read, if you go and read the stories of the Persian martyrs, stuff you read, volume one of the history of Christianity in Asia, there'll be some, there are some stories that are there to curl your toes.
Indeed, there are also two Persian bishops at the Council.
I see it nonetheless.
So there were a lot of Christians who still continue to be Christians within that Persian
empire despite zero Austrian persecution.
Yeah.
Well, before we take our second break, I just wanted to drop this on all the fans out there
who may not know this.
The world's most famous, Percy, Zowastrian of our time.
Freddie Mercury, the lead singer of Queen.
So on that bottom.
You have a sky burial.
I
I don't, I don't think so.
I'm not sure.
Anyway, take a second break.
The mains are pretty mercury.
And we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Ancient Near Eastern texts such as the Ball Cycle, who tray the pagan god Ball as a
rebel, the hero of a revolution, worshipped and glorified for his long string of victories.
In the Ball Book, a biography of the devil, Father Stephen D. Young shows that the Hebrew
scriptures consciously turn the Ball story on its head, depicting him as a failed and
and defeated rebel
who nonetheless tries to steal the glory that belongs to Almighty God.
From these scriptures, the figure of the devil emerged within Jewish and Christian tradition.
Father D. Yom works through the old and new testament passages that refer to various
ball stories, and he surveys ball worship through followers' beliefs, religious practices,
and liturgical life.
In these pages, we will see that the figures of Ball and the Devil, the Prince of...
of demons are one and the same.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.enchantface.com.
Again, that is store.enchantface.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF radio.
You know the way that he pronounced Bale in that I mean it's probably closer to correct.
You could do Bale, you could do Bale but Bale.
It kind of ruins all the puns.
Yes, Bale.
And he talks about Bale worship, the people could think were flat earthers.
Yes.
So someone wrote it in apparently and I checked, Freddie Mercury was cremated.
so
I don't know, is that blasphemous?
I don't know, pointing.
It is kind of disappointing.
There's some wild stuff going on in the chat, though.
There's one fellow that's saying that Stonehenge was built
by Phoenicians under the rule of King Solomon.
So is this one of these Lebanese folks
who just wants to take credit for everything?
I mean, I don't fault them for that.
I don't fault them for that.
But also I mean he's also...
I was also saying that some theory about Zoroastrianism
arising under frankly Jewish influence in the Persian Empire
that it...
I'm sure you've heard of that idea.
What do you think of that?
Well no, that just seems to be an inversion of the...
Yeah.
I mean, that's a no-you, right?
Like the common scholarly theory is that all this stuff
Second Table Judaism came from Persian.
Really right. And so that's just saying no you yeah. Yeah. No, it actually okay from Judaism
No, I mean, I don't see how you get psychedelic drug use and all this stuff from Judy right
Yeah
I see how you get it from Hinduism, but I don't see how you get it from
I mean just because things are similar doesn't mean that their one is derived from the other you know correlation
Does not equal
Causation and again, then they're not even that similar
Right!
Right
Yep, yep, yep. I mean to get to similar stuff you have to really
You have to be like well
rituals involving water
Right and you will cycle of feasts. I mean
Everyone has rituals involving water. Yeah, everyone has annual cycle you have to take it out to such a level of vagary that you're not really saying anything anymore
They eat bread weed bread
Yeah, exactly you know who else a bread eight-hole pit
Yeah, yeah, good times good times. Yeah, but we'll be talking a lot. I'm gonna do a teaser
Coming soon, not the next episode you're gonna hear
Which has already been recorded. There's gonna be some time you why me stuff happening with episodes folks. That's true. Get ready for it
but coming soon, an episode
about Mithras.
That's right.
Where you're going to find out that all those things that are like the same as Christianity
and Mithraism are phony.
I knew it.
So get ready for it.
Literally everything you've been told about Mithraism is wrong.
Except my favorite thing is like wrong like a lie, like a fabricated lie, like not a little
off base made up.
up. As I was telling you earlier
I like the fact that the guys on, well, maybe just Tom Holland on the rest of his history
podcast refers to myth.
Reism is basically the free masonry of the Roman Empire.
You know, yeah, a bunch of that is a little bit apropos.
Bunch of guys gathering together in some secret place, you know, making connections with
each other.
Secret.
Although it was especially popular in the military, which I don't know that Masonry is.
Yeah.
So all right.
We actually do have a couple of calls.
So we're going to go ahead.
It's one of the colors good in the other one evil.
Yes, I'm sure that's yes, we have a mannequin half medical dualism.
We have we have William, who is from a mountain top in Tennessee.
So he's called before welcome William.
Welcome back to Laura Spierts podcast.
Thank you, Oking of media.
And you can
killing a bar when you were only three.
I was actually five.
I was not exaggerated.
Okay.
That happened.
And you know, William, William was that was that loser con.
Laura's parents conference this last weekend.
So how are you doing?
I am doing very well.
Thank you.
Yep.
What's on your mind?
People call her.
So I had two questions.
One relating to Zora's Rhinism.
one relating to King Cyrus.
On the rest of the mechanism, he mentioned that it was not a very tolerant religion of other
religions.
Did it conceive of itself as a proselytizing religion, as a universal religion, and did
it once it's devotee to become a Loubber mentioned?
I don't know the answer to that, but I do know that now, this is my understanding, you have
to be born into it. And this is one of the reasons it's dwindling.
Is that you can't convert although I think maybe some groups do allow some conversions
But mostly they don't but I don't know if that's a later development or what
Do you know father are they yeah, they're so appetizing Zora Astrian's the ancient so no they didn't proselytize per se
the Zora Astrian practitioners
Were performing their duties on behalf of the world
world.
But the intolerance comes from they thought that other people practicing these other religious forms
interfered with like actively we're actively working against them.
So Christians by being Christians within the Persian Empire, their ritual life was actively working
against what the Zoroastrian state religion of the Sassanid Empire was trying to do.
And what they were trying to do was preserve justice and the world, right?
So they viewed Christians as this evil and malign corrupting element in society that needed to be eradicated.
And that's why they were so intolerant.
Yeah.
And in terms of uber mentioned, there seems to be literally no as much as I love it and listen to it in audio.
form and read it both at least once a year.
There seems to be no connection between
Ditch's Zerathustra and the historical Zerathustra.
Well, there you go.
What's your other question, William?
This one is on King Cyrus,
so you mentioned that he was a legendary figure
that Alexander modeled himself after.
But then after Alexander,
it seems that he was the one that people,
including Caesar Augustus wanted to...
who modeled themselves after, and this sort of mystic understanding of someone like an
Alexander or Julius Caesar or King Arthur, how did the figure of Cyrus evolve or persevere
from the classic Persian to the Parasyon to the Sassanid and then to the Islamic and period
and run us on zero.
How could you straight like a book about that, Father Stephen?
I mean, I got a long list.
To the age of eight.
Yeah, I mean, that's huge.
But he is.
So he does, he obviously, you know, as you mentioned, the
assassins, et cetera, are consciously trying to revive
Cyrus's recommended empire when they formed the second
person empire.
before it's wiped out. But I think the places where you see his legend and crop up is more figures like Tamerlane and
some of the other central Asian, right? I think that's sort of where his memory goes because as you mentioned, Alexander the Great in the Roman
imaginary as much as I hate to use that term.
the medieval and Renaissance Europe is hyper obsessed with Rome. Right. And so in that area
it fades. But I think in central Europe is where Cyrus continues to be seen as this sort of
foundational figure because he arises, you know, on the on the Persian plateau.
No.
B.
but he doesn't then go wet.
He's not a westerner or whatever.
He's not someone from outside of Asia
who comes in conquer Asia like Alexander.
He's an Asian who conquers elsewhere, right?
And remains Asian.
So I think that's the place really where his,
his status as a legendary in heroic figure more continues.
All right, well thank you very much for coming.
We're going to take one more call.
We have Barbara calling from Ohio.
Is it a high I see post falls?
Is there post falls in Ohio?
I know there's one in Idaho.
Yeah, no, it's Idaho.
Sorry.
You're an idol.
Mike, come on.
It's Idaho, not Ohio.
Those are not the same place.
State geography, my friend.
We should call out Mike on the year.
More than that.
I'm going to say that.
We should call out Mike on the ear more
often I feel like you might do a better job. Barbara, hello. Welcome to Laura's
guest. How often do people tell you they're coming to get you? I guess you don't get that
reference. Never mind. Go ahead. No, sorry. I'm saying it. But I really quick before I
I guess my question is, I guess your new...
book that you're going to do on SIRIS. Could you continue that to his representation in
the movie The Warriors? Because that would be great.
Yes. I'll even include a chapter on this hypothetical book that you'll never see on SIRIS,
The Virus, is portrayed by John Malkovich.
Okay. I don't even know that one.
Conair.
Okay, so I guess
My question actually doesn't have to do with another movie.
I just got back from watching John Aries in theaters
and something I've noticed in all the John movies
is that there's this connection that seems
to be really similar to the rastering of them, where
there's a creator who created things out of light
and he has clue, right?
It was like his shadow.
Who turns out to be the bad guy even and?
I think I would just curious about if you've noticed any connections between the
rasteranism and the movies Tron
I've only seen the first Tron movie and it was
the 80s I think when I saw it so I
Remember the Tron fights for the users
I first saw the movie Tron the original Tron
on.
uh, at Uncle Howie's Pizza.
Hey, projected onto a big screen, right?
Like it was the actual film reels projected out of big screened.
Uncle Howie's Pizza at a pizza party we had because we got second place in
second grade A Y S O soccer.
Wow. Thank you very much for the season.
Um, got a silver medal in everything.
Um,
But I have seen the other Tron movies. I haven't seen Aries yet, but I plan on it, but probably not till it goes to Disney Plus because leaders are expensive and I'm Dutch.
But I hadn't thought about it before, but I see what I see what you're I'm picking up what you're laying down. I see what you're saying here.
And I think I think there are some elements. I think there are some elements there.
See, I thought you were going to do this whole Pajot AI thing and I was going to have to
poo poo it.
But I will do no poo pooing.
Because yeah, I think that, obviously, you know, you could push it too far.
There's no sky burials, right?
And I guess there were kind of hallucinogens, there were drugs sort of in the second one.
So yeah, there might be something there.
might be something.
there. I don't know who wrote Tron. Or any of the sequels. But there are some elements.
Now, there may, the tough thing would be differentiating what zero asterion, what's
Manicky and what's just kind of Gnostic. But there's a confluence of ideas there, I think,
in Tron that I think you're right about.
Well.
I hope that helps on some of the barmer. It's a tricky idea. I mean, why do you got doing a rewatch of the first two before I see Aries?
So now I'm going to be thinking about this while I so maybe I'll report back in a future episode.
Yeah. Yeah. I have to give them all a watch. It's been many, many, it's probably been, I don't know, 40 years since I saw the original one.
So the second one is the rare one where that digital D aging really works because they're supposed to be computer programs.
Right, right so the fact that it looks kind of CGI a digital like works
It should be right. Yeah, it shouldn't look perfect
Okay, Valley works in your favor. All right. Well, thank you very much for calling Barbara
Okay, you guys
Yeah, you're welcome
Well, we promised we promised another Messiah
Yeah.
That's true.
But you know, I wonder if she would have gotten the reference if I'd said it.
as, you know, they're coming to get you, Bob, or, uh,
see, I'm not sure if he's on the line, so she can't tell us.
Yeah. Yeah. I don't know. I mean, that's one of the classic movie lines of all time.
And it's October, but anyway, I guess she's lived a charmed life not having like
goons like me, fall around and say that in high school or something. So
fair enough.
So yes, Cyrus in the Bible, what we were actually going to talk about tonight,
Let's get to it!
more than two hours in. Yes.
This is our want. So there are a few places where Cyrus pops up in the Bible. The first one
is just mentioning one of the very important things he did,
Biblically speaking, and that's in 2 Chronicles 36, verses 22 and 23.
Yeah. This is the very end of 2 Chronicles, starting with verse 22.
Now in the first year of Cyrus King
of Persia that the word of the Lord by the mouth of Jeremiah might be fulfilled.
The Lord stirred up the spirit of Cyrus King of Persia so that he made a proclamation throughout
all his kingdom and also put it in writing. Thus says Cyrus King of Persia, the Lord the
God of heaven has given me all the kingdoms of the earth and he has charged me to build
him a house of Jerusalem which is in Judah. Whoever is among you of all his people may the
Lord his God be with him, let him go up. So I mean, this is the basically the ending of
the exile right?
Right, so this is the end of the exile.
But notice that this is the next thing we read is gonna expand on this even more
But notice the motivation here is not just like you know
Oh, why did those pesky Babylonians those meanies make all these Jews come here to Mesopotamia?
Let's let them go home
He's sending them back in order to rebuild the temple
So, this is how this is framed.
Right, that's the purpose for it.
So he's...
what he literally says there is Yahweh wants a temple built for him in Jerusalem. So, hey, any
of you people who are from there who want to head back and do it, go for it. Yeah, exactly.
So that's a little bit of a different causal chain than the way we normally think about it.
It's not that he gets a petition. Oh, hey, there's a new emperor. Let's petition him and see if
See if you'll let us go home.
No, it's...
it's God's doing and it's for the purpose of building the temple. But this gets expanded
upon at the beginning of the book of Ezra. Yeah, which in a lot of Bibles is literally the very
next thing in the Bible. Okay. Ezra chapter 1 verses 1 through 11. In the first year of Cyrus
King of Persia, that the word of the Lord by the mouth of Jeremiah by people filled, the Lord
stirred up the spirit of Cyrus King of Persia so that he made a proclamation throughout all his
was kingdom and also put it in writing.
This is almost exactly this.
Same.
Thus says Cyrus King of Persia,
The Lord the God of Heaven has given me all the kingdoms of the earth and he has charged
me to build him a house at Jerusalem which is in Judah.
Whoever is among you of all his people may his God be with him and let him go up to Jerusalem
which is in Judah and rebuild the house of the Lord the God of Israel, he is the God who
is in Jerusalem and let each survivor in whatever place he sojourns be assisted by the men
of his place with silver and gold with goods and with beasts besides free will offerings
for the house of
God that is in Jerusalem.
Then rose up the heads of the Father's houses of Judah and Benjamin, and the priests
and the Levites, everyone whose spirit God had stirred to go up to rebuild the house of
the Lord that is in Jerusalem.
And all who were about them aided them with vessels of silver, with gold, with goods,
with beasts, and with costly wares besides all that was freely offered.
Cyrus the King also brought out the vessels of the Lord, vessels of the house of the Lord
that Nebuchadnezzar had carried away from Jerusalem and placed in the house of his gods.
Cyrus King of Persia brought these out in the charge of Mithradath, the treasurer, who
counted them out to Shesh Bazar, the Prince of Judah.
And I would unreccommon naming your kid that.
And this was the number of them.
Thirty basins of gold, thousand bases of silver, 29 sensors, 30 bowls of gold, 400 dead bowls
of silver, and a thousand other vessels.
All the vessels of gold and silver were 5,400.
All these that Shesh Bazar bring up and the exiles were brought up from Babylonia.
to Jerusalem. It is fun to say Shash Bazar though. Yeah, all the kids calling him Shash.
What up Shash? Yeah, yeah, so bad. As. As. As. Popular last name among.
It's true. Middle East folk. We know a few. So, as you noted, the beginning of
The answer is verbatim, the end of...
or second Chronicles.
Confounding that even more,
if you know that the Greek Old Testament tradition,
there's actually another book called First Ezra
that is in between in the Greek
that is literally a chunk of the book of Ezra
and a chunk of second Chronicles swished together.
Yeah.
That is in their in addition to second Chronicles
and canonical Ezra.
Yeah.
So they got together and had a baby.
with that.
topic for another episode. Yes. There's another episode. We used to do that all the time.
We'd be like, someday we'll do an episode. Well, we're starting that again, apparently,
because you've already gotten promised to a myth or is an episode. And now I'm talking about
doing a books of Ezra episode, because there's like four of them. That would be fun.
So, but we shall see. But for now, right? Basically, what we get here, that is more detail,
that not only does he...
send them back to build the temple, but he hauls out all the stuff from the temple that
Nebuchadnezzar stole and gives it back essentially, sort of officially by way of his treasurer
to the heir to the throne of Judah.
But again, the purpose is to build
is to build this temple, right?
And he's sending them back to do it.
And so the idea here is that Cyrus has been so moved
by God that he wants a temple rebuilt so that sacrifices can be offered to Yahweh the God of Israel on his behalf.
And we talked about how this was his general religious sort of paradigm.
This is how he approached religions.
So that's sort of the key historical importance for the story of the Old Testament of Cyrus.
He's the one who allows them to go back from exile.
He puts an end to the exile.
He not only permits, but facilitates the rebuilding of the temple in Jerusalem.
He does these things.
That's the historical element.
there. There's also then a theological element to this. And this comes from what is a fairly well-known
passage in Isaiah. On Isaiah, it's the end of chapter 44, the beginning of chapter 45 now. So a word
about Isaiah before we read it. Okay, so this is in part of Isaiah that your...
Or Randall Oltessa with scholars will tell you is Dutero, Isaiah.
That may be just one of two parts of Isaiah, or if they're really nasty, then there will
also be a Tritoo, Isaiah, a third Isaiah.
Now there's two elements to this, and we have to distinguish these.
They don't necessarily.
We
should. So there are features in the text of the book of Isaiah, which is a very long book
in the Old Testament, in its canonical form. There are features
that look like breaks of the text at the end of chapter 3, at least at the end of chapter 39.
I think the other one is the one between
quote-unquote second and third Isaiah is more iffy.
But there's definitely a disjunction at the end of chapter 30.
I'd be getting 40. That's why they put the chapter break there.
When they were putting in the chapter breaks. They were looking for things in the text where there are natural
breaks or topic changes and that kind of thing. And there just, there is a break there.
Okay.
And you can even take that break and say, you know, this looks like a significant break.
a significant break.
And in the book of Isaiah, if we take what the book of Isaiah actually says, right, seriously,
book of Isaiah does not claim that Isaiah sat down and wrote it.
The book of Isaiah claims that Isaiah had disciples, the prophet Isaiah had disciples, that they
wrote down all his prophecies and after his death, they collected them.
And the book of Isaiah that we have now is his disciples collection.
of his prophecies. That is that that should be a problem for any Christian, right? Because that's how the
gospels were written, right? Jesus didn't write them personally, right? Pen to paper, right? So that's
just saying Isaiah came together like that. So the idea that at some point there were two different
collections or even three different collections of Isaiah's prophecies and that they all got brought
together into what is now the book of
Isaiah, again, should not be a big problem for us. Right? Like, when you read the book of
Psalms, there are five books within the book of Psalms. Like, we know that there were previous
collections of Psalms that all got brought together into what we now call the book of
Psalms. It's not a big deal, right? That's cool. Right? So if that's true about Isaiah,
that there is a quote unquote,
Dutero's Isaiah because there were two different collections.
and those two were put together to make what we now call the Bhagavad-gīsa, that's totally cool.
Here's the other piece though. Okay. The other piece is the reason most scholars want to talk about
Dūtaro and Tridu-Azēa is that they want to say they were written at different people at different
people at different times. And the reason they want to say that is not because of any internal
evidence.
or even at the external evidence, the reason they want to say that is because
texts within Dutero and Trito Isaiah
predict things that hadn't happened yet
when the first part of Isaiah was written.
And they come to the text with the presupposition that this text cannot possibly predict the future.
right like a guess right like it
could say, you know, oh, you're doing great now, Babylon, but you're, you're
going to one of these days, right? Like you could do that, right? But for
example, the text we're about to read, the chapter four to four and 45 that
mentioned Cyrus by name. Yeah, no, no, no, that you. That's not
possible. That can't possibly have been written before before he showed up.
Therefore, right, this part of Isaiah has to have been written in the Persian
period.
long after the original Isaiah was dead. And then based on that, they go looking for
disjunctions in the text, right? To say, ah, see, here's a disjunction in the
text at the end of chapter 39. See, this is a separate section. See, this was
written later. Then you ask, well, what's your evidence that this was written
later, what they point to is the disjunction in the text. But that is
The production of the text doesn't prove it was written later.
Doesn't prove anything.
It suggests that maybe there were two separate collections that were put together, but it
doesn't mean anything in terms of the respective time in which those two sections were written.
They could have been collected, written, collected at the same time, and then brought together
at a later point.
The fact that there were at one point two separate pieces does not mean that one piece
was written centuries after the other.
And the only thing that would suggest that it was written centuries after the other is
if you assume the impossibility of predicting the future.
Right.
So this is a basic problem.
You can see this unfold over and over again in old testament scholarship.
You bring some presupposition to the text.
The presupposition of the text requires you to argue.
XYZ, you find apostereory, you find things which make what you want to believe based on your
presuppositions possible. And then you argue from those things, you say that those things you found
are arguments for your presupposition. Even though the whole order of your logic was entirely
the opposite.
And that's how you do bad scholarship. But so the text we're about to read from
Dutero Isaiah is going to mention Cyrus by name. And we're going to see it's very
specific about Cyrus, the Persian Empire, Persian religion even very specific ways
before the fact. Now the Jewish tradition is firmly that Isaiah wrote this. This was
already around.
and that this was shown by exiles to Cyrus,
and that reading this text with his name in it
is what led Cyrus to make the proclamations we just read about.
Hmm.
That's the Jewish tradition regarding it.
Yeah, yeah.
That.
Which kind of explains why the Jews in particular
get sent back, right?
I mean, the religious tolerance thing,
Yeah, that was everybody.
but he didn't go moving people around a lot.
He didn't go endowing red-dotemples a lot.
Right.
But so let's go ahead and we'll discuss it a little more
and read this chunk of Isaiah.
Okay.
Starting with verse 24 of chapter 44.
Thus says the Lord your Redeemer who formed you from the womb.
I am the Lord who made all things who loan stretched out the heaven
who spread out the earth by myself, who frustrates the signs of liars, and makes fools of
diviners, who turns wise men back and makes their knowledge foolish, who confirms the word of
his servant and fulfills the counsel of his messengers, who says of Jerusalem she shall be inhabited,
and of the cities of Judah they shall be built, and I will raise up their ruins, who says to the
deep, be dry, I will draw up your rivers, who says of Cyrus he is my shepherd, and he shall fulfill
all my purpose. Saying of Jerusalem she sh-
shall be built, and of the temple your foundation shall be laid.
Now Isaiah 45, thus says the Lord to his anointed, to Cyrus, whose right hand I have grasped,
to subdue nations before him, and to loose the belts of kings, to open doors before him
that gates may not be closed, I will go before you and level the exalted places.
I will break in pieces the doors of bronze and cut through the bars of iron.
I will give you the treasures of darkness in the hordes and secret places that you may
We know that it is I the Lord, the God of Israel, who call you by your name.
For the sake of my servant Jacob and Israel my chosen, I call you by your name.
I name you, though you do not know me.
I am the Lord, and there is no other.
Besides me there is no God.
I equip you, though you do not know me, that people may know from the rising of the sun
and from the west.
But there is none besides me.
I am the Lord, and there is no other.
I form light and create darkness.
I make well-being and create calamity.
I am the Lord who does all these things.
Right, so you may have noticed a few things in there.
Right.
So obviously there's a mention of Cyrus by name.
Notice when he's first mentioned at the end of chapter 44,
he's referred to as God's shepherd.
Think about parodotus's story.
Yeah.
And again, that in particular he's called to rebuild the temple, right?
And then in chapter 45, right, when it says, thus says the Lord to his anointed to Cyrus,
it literally says in the Hebrew, thus says Yahweh to his Messiah to Cyrus.
Yeah.
Messiah, the word for Mashiach, the word for anointed one, right?
And we mentioned this, I think briefly in our episode on just the Messiah.
in general, right, that we as Christians, right, because we're after the fact we're like,
well, there's one Messiah, and it's Jesus, Jesus Christ, Jesus the Messiah, right? But before
that, Messiah was more flexible. We talked about how they believed it, a priestly Messiah,
a kingly Messiah, Messiah Ben David, the Messiah Ben Joseph.
They were the one, right, these different traditions of anointed ones.
Right, and so here we see even Cyrus
Right who did not convert to Judaism
Right he was not circumcised he did not eat the puzzle right
Certainly the temple to be rebuilt certainly at sacrifices offered to Yahweh his name
But was also having sacrifices to Marduk offered in his name and right everyone else
He is anointed for a particular purpose right by God
That is doing those things, right?
Doing those things.
And that God brings him into the position he's in
so that he can then do those things.
But notice also, right, when you get into
down to verse 5, sorry, in verse 5 of chapter 45,
right, we says, I am Lord, I am Yahweh.
There is no other beside me.
There is no God, right?
I equip you though you do
do not know me talking to Cyrus. Cyrus does not know him. Right. So this is not because
Cyrus was a follower of Yahweh, right? But notice, he says that people may know from the
rising of the sun and from the west, right, from one end of your empire to the other,
right, from the east to the west, there is none beside, none beside me. I am Yahweh.
There is no other.
and then notice specifically in verse seven what he claims. Now what? I form light and create darkness.
What's that a reference to?
Yeah.
Hurrah Mazda, right?
Yeah. I create light and create the other one.
Yes, corrective.
And then number two, and let me translate this, right?
Father Andrew Red translation that says, I bake well being and create calamity. And that's a valid
translation, but let me be more provocative.
in the translation, I make good and create evil.
There's another way of translating the Hebrew.
Although the word ray that's raised that's translated there is evil can also mean famine
like trouble calamity bad things. But the idea here being it's not a hermazdan his shadow.
It's all Yahweh the God of Israel. Right.
that he says, I am Yahweh. Who does
all these things. That's not someone else doing any of this. Right? So he is at once sort
of claiming Cyrus as his own goddess and repudiating, right? Cyrus is sense of who Cyrus is.
Hmm, right.
Cyrus is not...
the king of the four quarters of the world. Right? Cyrus is the servant of the
God who rules the four quarters of the world. A God who he doesn't even know, but
whom he's serving anyway. Right? But whom he's serving anyway. So one past
explanation of this text based on the Jewish tradition I mentioned,
you
that they showed this to Cyrus to get DeRigga back,
is that this was fabricated by the exiles,
by the Jewish exiles.
Huh.
That they inserted this to flatter Cyrus
to get him to send the back, right?
But let me suggest based on what we just read,
if you really understand it,
it's not actually flattering to Cyrus.
Yeah, it's correcting him.
Yes.
It is.
demoting Cyrus to his proper place. But he the only the God of Israel. So maybe having his name
appear at the sacred books by you know, impress him. But this is not the kind of thing you would
fabricate if you were trying to ingratiate yourself. Right. That that unwork you there. That
That doesn't work either.
So.
If you're just willing to accept that it's possible that the prophet Isaiah had some few something in the future, like a name revealed them, then there's a very simple explanation for all this.
Otherwise, feel free to do all the mental gymnastics you feel like you need to try to explain this text and Cyrus's actions in history.
Yeah.
So I think.
You know, connecting both our previous episode, the Nebuchadnezzar episode and this one,
you know, both these are cases of great kings who are used by God to accomplish things
that God wants.
Of course, in Nebuchadnezzar's case, Nebuchadnezzar gets radically humbled as part of what's
going on there and Cyrus doesn't have that experience, although there's a little bit
going on of that, you know, in this last text that we read here, you know, it's correct
in going on. And I think for me, the through line, I mean, there's multiple possible through
lines, I guess, but the through line that really comes to me at the moment is, you know,
that God is always working to establish justice, to bring things in order, to bring his people
Israel where they need to be in faithfulness to him.
And of course, it's not just...
a story about that, something that happened in the past, but it's also a story about us,
right? So, you know, looking at these two kings, we can see, okay, I think that this is who I am,
what I'm doing in the world, and then here's this message from God that says, actually, you need to
do this, and this is not who you are, you're that, and I can take that as a correction and obey
and become faithful. And I mean, my experience is that for a lot of the Christian life, most of
its relatively gentle like.
that. You know, you hear a sermon and it might convict you, but your your priest is not going to come out and,
and you know, personally pressure you or make bad things happen to you. If, if you know, obey,
it's mostly going to be up to you to determine whether you're going to obey or not. It's up to you
when you hear the hymns of the church to obey or not, right? But then there's sometimes in life
where you have to kind of experience a nebuchadnezzar. Most of us are not transformed into a kind of
I don't know, where will sort of thing, but there certainly can be experiences of great
humiliation, great humbling.
And it seems like life has fallen completely apart.
I mean, nebuchadnezzar lost everything.
He became like an animal for a long time.
And we don't want that, right?
But I think it's one of the great themes of the Orthodox Christian tradition, which is
humble yourself.
or God is going to humble you. You know, and you have a choice. You can humble yourself. You can live
faithfully. You can always be examining the way you're living and ask, is this in alignment with
what the scriptures say? Is this in alignment with what all the teaching and tradition of church says?
or do I have some changes I need to make?
I mean it's true, God loves you just...
the way that you are, he does. He loves you because he created you and you are created
according to his image. But the way that he loves you is not going to leave you the way
you are. And it's up to you to accept that transformative love and to become an alignment
with him because because love does that love. You know, love is a relationship. It's
There's a given take going on and so there's
a transformation that occurs. God has already accepted to become human for our
sakes. And so what we need to do in response is accept to become deified because of
his great love for us. And what we see in these two kings, Nebuchadnezzar and
Cyrus, is that no matter where you are, you can meet the very top of the most
powerful thing in the world. And both of them were in their times. And yet
Thank you.
You still are under God.
God is still the one who's in charge.
And the only reason that you have that position at all
is because God has given it to you.
And while probably no one listening to this podcast
is the head of an empire,
we all have things that God has given to us.
And the reality is it can be taken away very, very quickly
in one way or another, it could be a financial disaster,
it could be natural disaster,
that could be a health.
disaster and can all go. So the question is really what are you going to do with what you got?
And yeah, so those are my kind of main takeaways from these last two episodes.
So, Cyrus, who we talked about tonight, was the king of the world.
Not in the my new girlfriend is about to show me off her.
rafted drown sense, but in the literal sense. And accomplished a fair amount, shall we
say, in his 70 years of life. Pretty much nobody. I want to say pretty much nobody. I don't
think even Alexander the Great can really match his list of achievements because he didn't
get to rule over what he conquered.
And yet, and yet, now, as we're celebrating this, what was it, 2653rd anniversary of his
conquest of Babylon on Sunday, there's only really one thing that he's remembered for by
the vast majority of people in the world who have heard of him at all.
And that's letting the Jewish people go back to Judah.
And that's despite how that all turned out, which wasn't well.
And how short lived all that ended up being and that being just this one
turning point in the story of Israel. God's people as a whole.
It's that one thing.
And...
As the prophet Isaiah presents it, the whole purpose for God creating him and God guiding
him and God appointing him to be the one who became the king of the world was so that
he would be able to do that one thing so that when the moment came he could do that one
thing that God had prepared for him to do.
Not just me tonight, but St. Paul a long time ago said that the same is true for you and me.
That there are good works that God prepared in advance for us to do, not in a general sense.
for me to do, for you to do, right?
That in God's Providence, right?
I was born at a certain time and God gave me certain gifts and certain experiences in my life and a certain education and certain things so that I would be in certain places at certain times to be able to do certain things that he wanted me to do and that were truly important.
They're truly important.
And the purpose of my life, what will give my life purpose.
is if I take those moments and I do those things. God doesn't need me to do them. He can get
somebody else to do them. Right? But if I make him do that, if I opt out, they say it's
not gonna be God's problem, they'll still get done.
But there goes the purpose.
there goes the meaning in my life. There's a lot of sermon drawing from certain quarters of the
internet about meaning and finding meaning, feeling like we have meaning and purpose.
And I think a lot of people are looking for meaning in some kind of philosophical sense or some kind
of broad arc or some kind of career path or some kind of big thing.
And according to scriptures and even the example of Cyrus, that's not where it's actually
found.
The whole thing may be found at one moment.
Everything in your life may be preparing you for one moment where there's one thing you
need to do.
One thing you need to say.
place you need to be for somebody else.
And you being there at that moment and doing it, that's what the meaning was, that's what
the purpose was.
And you say, well, that's not much of a purpose, that's not much of a meaning, just one little
thing at one time.
But you see, there's a chain reaction of those little things, right?
Because I'm in the right place at the right time and say the right thing to somebody else
and then that person.
Because of it, becomes equipped at some future moment with someone else to say or to do something
that needs to be set or done.
And through that chain reaction, that's how Christ's church grows in the world, that's
how salvation spreads through the world, that's how the knowledge of God spreads through the
world, that's how the world is redeemed.
by a series of chain reactions from just regular people doing the things that got
has prepared them and equipped them to do when the time comes. And so if you're one of those
folks who's sitting around wondering or wondering, right? Why am I here? What is this all about? Why am I
still alive? Right? What is the purpose? What is the point? Right? You're not going to find it by
by sitting there wondering.
You're not going to find it by musing philosophically.
You're not going to find it by having a long series of
interminable philosophical discussions about it on YouTube.
That's for sure.
You're not going to find it by watching smart people talk
about it incessantly on YouTube.
Even if I'm one of those people you think is a smart person
talking about it.
You're not going to find it watching my videos.
I'm going to put it in the middle of the screen.
It's in the middle of the screen.
Find it by going out and living your life.
You're gonna find it by going using the gifts
that God's given you, by being an active part
of your family, your parish, your workplace, your school.
And being on the lookout for those moments,
those moments where you're the one who's prepared to help.
You're the one who's ready to say what needs to be said
or to listen or to do what needs to be done
and then doing it.
And you may not instantly know when you did it that, ah, there it was.
There was the moment.
Now my life has meaning in purpose, right?
May take some time.
May take some time for that chain reaction to loop back around and for you to see what's
going on, right?
But that sense of purpose, that sense of meaning, that's where it's found.
So even though this may make some of the extra-path people mad at me,
STO-
Stop listening to podcasts and go out there if you're life now.
You just wasted like probably close to three hours, right?
Go do some things, right?
And you'll find what you're looking for in becoming the person who God created you to be.
Well, that's our show for tonight.
Thank you very much for listening, everybody.
If you didn't happen to get through to us live, we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsNationFate.com, you can message us on our Facebook page, leave
us a voice mail and speakpipe.com slash LordofSpirits or you know, show up toward our conferences
which we just had this last weekend.
If you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity though or you need to help finding
a parish which is where we actually do this thing called Christianity, head over to
to orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcasts
on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month.
at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
I hopped off the plane at LAX with a dream in my cardigan.
Welcome to the land of fame, excess.
Am I going to fit in?
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page.
You can join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings
and share the show with a friend.
And finally, be sure to go to www.AxerFate.com.
Stoke Support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Jump to the cab.
Here I am for the first time.
Look to my right and I see the Hollywood sign.
This is also crazy.
Everybody see.
so famous. Thank you, goodnight, God bless you all.
voice worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and strength
and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.